<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Certain proposals humbly offered, for the preservation &amp; continuance of the truly reformed Protestant religion, in these three kingdomes of England, Scotland and Ireland by a professor of the said truly reformed Protestant religion ...</title>
            <author>J. B.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1674</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 116 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 20 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A31087</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing B96</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R11223</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">11994955</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 11994955</idno>
            <idno type="VID">52086</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A31087)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 52086)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 856:21)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Certain proposals humbly offered, for the preservation &amp; continuance of the truly reformed Protestant religion, in these three kingdomes of England, Scotland and Ireland by a professor of the said truly reformed Protestant religion ...</title>
                  <author>J. B.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 35 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>s.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[S.l. :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1674.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Bodleian Library.</note>
                  <note>The epistle to the reader signed: J.B.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Protestants --  Great Britain.</term>
               <term>Protestantism.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-05</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Megan Marion</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:52086:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>CERTAIN PROPOSALS Humbly Offered, FOR THE PRESERVATION &amp; CONTINUANCE Of the truly Reformed PROTESTANT RELIGION, In theſe Three Kingdomes of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>By a Profeſſor of the ſaid Truly Reformed Proteſtant-Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and greatly ſolicitous for the preſervation of it.</p>
            <p>Printed in the Year 1674.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:52086:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:52086:2"/>
            <head>THE EPISTLE TO THE READER.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Chriſtian Reader,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>VVHen I ſeriouſly conſider the preſent State of the tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Reformed Proteſtant Religion, as abroad through<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the whole <hi>European</hi> world, ſo particularly here at home in theſe three Kingdoms of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland;</hi> my heart is ſad within me, and my Spirit even fails to think what dark and diſmal things are coming upon us; and therefore for the better eaſing of my own mind, and the declaring of a willingneſs at leaſt, to do ſomething (if poſſible) for the preventing of what I fear, I have adventured to publiſh this enſuing Treatiſe; which though there be not one word in it (that as I humbly conceive) can give any juſt ground of offence to any true Proteſtant, of what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever Rank or Quality, or of whatſoever Party, whether <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſt</hi> or <hi>Nonconformiſt;</hi> yet times of Trading for Books, as well as for other Commodities, being very dead and diſcouraging, I find none are willing to adventure upon the charge of printing this ſmall Copy, elſe it had come out long ſince. At laſt therefore rather than it ſhould lie ſtifled in the birth any longer, and my la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour, and the end of it ſhould be wholly loſt, I have made hard ſhift thus to obſtetricate and bring it forth at my own Charge. Money doth not at all abound with me, but the quite contrary; ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving divers both unavoidable and expenſive cares upon me; yet ſuch is the vehemency of my deſire to uſe the utmoſt endeavour that lies in me, for the ſervice of Chriſt, even beyond my poor capaci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, and for the good of my Native Countrey, that I have devoted
<pb facs="tcp:52086:3"/>
this Impreſſion (ſo much of it as turns not to any account towards my reimburſement) to be freely given to ſuch as will but vouchſafe to read it, and when they have done, propagate it into good hands, though they ſhould not be willing themſelves to ſpare a ſmall piece of Silver to purchaſe it. Perhaps the Lord will be pleaſed to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept and bleſs my Deſign therein, it may be he will ſmile upon it, and render it ſome way profitable to the end for which it is intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed; in the hope whereof I reſt: and however it ſucceds, ſhall qui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>et my ſelf in this, that I have done my endeavour in the ſight of God and mine own Conſcience, to ſerve thè Generation wherein I live. And ſo having thus far expreſſed my care and ſolicitude for the next Age, and hereby made thee a witneſs of it, I ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe my ſelf what I truly am,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Thine and my Countreys moſt affectionately earneſt Well-wiſher and Servant in Chriſt, <hi>J. B.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:52086:3"/>
            <head>Certain Propoſals humbly offered for the Preſervation and Continuance of the truly Reformed Proteſtant Religion down to ſucceeding Ages.</head>
            <p>HOw deplorable a caſe the <hi>truly Reformed Proteſtant Religion</hi> now is in, partly from the power and prevalency of <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry, Arminianiſm, Socinianiſm, Quakeriſm</hi> (an Hotch-potch of all the reſt) and many other dangerous Errors and Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtitions; partly by reaſon of the <hi>Death of great numbers</hi> of the moſt Learned, Pious, Zealous, Faithful and Painful Miniſters in theſe <hi>Kingdomes;</hi> partly from the want of a due care to provide ſuch as may <hi>ſucceed</hi> them in after-Ages, by ſuch a <hi>liberal Education</hi> of the Youth of the preſent Age, as might fit them for that <hi>Service;</hi> and laſtly, by the general and univerſal <hi>Prophaneneſs</hi> that every where ſpreads it ſelf among us: I ſay, how deplorable a caſe the ſaid <hi>truly Reformed Proteſtant Religion</hi> is now in, by the means aforeſaid, and ſome others that might be added, would fill up a huge Volumn to declare: a Work which I ſhall not here undertake; but ſhall rather apply my ſelf humbly to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pound <hi>ſuch wayes</hi> and <hi>means,</hi> as by the Bleſſing of God may <hi>revive</hi> and <hi>reſtore</hi> the ſaid <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> out of that deplorable ſtate in which it ſeems now to lie <hi>bleeding,</hi> as it were, to death, and in ſome places almoſt ready to give up the Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>But among many <hi>Propoſals</hi> which I had prepared, and intended to have offered, I have ſingled out only theſe three, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That an <hi>hearty <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> at leaſt, in Love and Affection, between all <hi>Diſsenting Parties</hi> in matters of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> that are other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſound and orthodox in the <hi>Doctrinals</hi> and holy <hi>Practicks</hi> of the right Reformed <hi>Proteſtant Religion,</hi> be heartily endeavoured.</p>
            <p>Now this will be found principally among four ſorts of <hi>Proteſtant-Profeſſors</hi> in <hi>England;</hi> the <hi>Epiſcopal, Presbyterian, Congregational,</hi> and ſuch of the moderate and ſober-minded <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> (ſo called) as differ only in the point of <hi>Infant-Baptiſm.</hi> I name the <hi>Epiſcopal-Proteſtant-Profeſſor</hi> with the other three, becauſe I know ſome of them to be men of eminent Learning and Piety, and in all the main Points of <hi>Proteſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm</hi> very <hi>ſound.</hi> Thouſands (I doubt not) both Miniſters and People
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:52086:4" rendition="simple:additions"/>
of the Church of <hi>England</hi> (ſo called) are of the ſame Judgment and Practice with our famouſly Holy and Learned Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> publiſhed in his excellent Book, entituled, <hi>The Sum and Subſtance of Chriſtian-Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion.</hi> And why ſhould not both <hi>Preſbyterians, Catapaedobaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Congregational</hi> men (ſo I had rather ſtyle them, than by the odious Name of <hi>Independents</hi>) have as real and hearty good will to theſe as to any other? Was not the Blood of Chriſt ſhed for <hi>them?</hi> Was not Heaven founded as much for <hi>them</hi> as for any? For <hi>ſuch of them,</hi> I mean, as are under the ſame Spirit of <hi>True Faith</hi> and <hi>Repentance,</hi> which the Goſpel requires in all that ſhall be ſaved. As for joyning with them in Matters of Worſhip, where <hi>Conſcience</hi> is not ſatisfied, I by no means perſwade any to it; <hi>I cannot do it my ſelf:</hi> yet I truly love many that do, becauſe I am bound in Charity to think they follow their Light, whilſt I ſee them otherwiſe walking in an <hi>uniform Tenour of Holineſs,</hi> both within doors and without, throughout the whole courſe of their Lives.</p>
            <p>The other three, namely, the <hi>Presbyterian, Antipedobaptiſts</hi> and <hi>Congregational,</hi> if they do but keep cloſe to their <hi>own declared Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> on each ſide, that is, That none be admitted into their Churches, that in a true Goſpel-ſence are <hi>ignorant</hi> and <hi>ſcandalous</hi> (for by that, thoſe that <hi>diſcern not the Lord's Body,</hi> are <hi>ignorant,</hi> and thoſe that live not holily, are <hi>ſcandalous</hi>) I ſee no reaſon but <hi>(ſalvis utrinque principiis)</hi> they may allow each others to be the true Churches of Chriſt. Both ſides prove their Miniſtry to be from Chriſt, and to have the <hi>Eſſentials</hi> of an <hi>Inſtitution</hi> in it; one Party making the Formality of his <hi>External Call</hi> to conſiſt in the Election of the People only, with a <hi>ſolemn Dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation</hi> to their Work by Faſting and Prayer; the other Party granting this to be requiſite, but withal requiring the addition of <hi>Hands impo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by a Presbytery;</hi> which by the former is not eſteemed neceſſary. And then for <hi>Synods;</hi> both Parties approve of them as uſeful and needful for <hi>mutual</hi> and <hi>common Advice,</hi> though they differ in the Point of <hi>Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction,</hi> and the <hi>proper ſeat</hi> and extent of it.</p>
            <p>Now why may not a <hi>Brotherly Amity</hi> well conſiſt with theſe Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rences, ſince on neither ſide any <hi>eſſential thing</hi> is wanting to render them true Miniſters and Churches of Chriſt; and ſuch as for the <hi>moſt part</hi> do otherwiſe agree in all matters of <hi>Doctrine</hi> and <hi>Practice?</hi> Nay, why may they not ſo far mutually agree, as to walk together in <hi>holy Fellowſhip</hi> one Church with another, as occaſions ſerve, the Members of one Church communicating with the Members of the other? How ſad is it, that where the way for a cloſure lies ſo <hi>fair and eaſie,</hi> good men
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:52086:4"/>
ſhould ſtand at ſo great a diſtance, for ſo long a time, each from other? What <hi>bitterneſs,</hi> what <hi>angry reflections,</hi> what <hi>unbrotherly exaſperations</hi> are ſtill found between theſe <hi>differing Parties?</hi> Whence comes it? Is it not from the <hi>Devil,</hi> the great <hi>Author</hi> and <hi>Fomenter</hi> of all Diviſions? When ſhall the Spirit of <hi>Meekneſs, Plain-heartedneſs</hi> and <hi>True Christian Love</hi> put an end to theſe <hi>Wranglings?</hi> When ſhall it once be? Why ſhould any, on one ſide or the other, remain under their own <hi>Paſſions, Prejudices</hi> and <hi>inflexible Moroſities?</hi> Is there not great cauſe to ſuſpect that <hi>Carnal Policy, Self-opiniativeneſs, Pride of Heart,</hi> or ſomething worſe, lies at the bottom? Is it poſſible, that where <hi>Sincerity, Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>Gracious Diſpoſition</hi> as alwayes is accompanied more or leſs, with the <hi>Sweet Spirit</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> ſhould dwell long in any that are true Members of him? Who can be ſaid truly to have learned of him, that are not <hi>like</hi> him in the Grace of <hi>Meekneſs</hi> and <hi>Lowlineſs</hi> of heart? Sure if any thing in the world be juſt matter of <hi>Wonder,</hi> this is, that <hi>no endeavours</hi> hitherto us'd, no, nor no <hi>ſevere Providences</hi> from God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, can reconcile <hi>Brethren,</hi> that have <hi>coſt Chriſt ſo dear,</hi> are ſo <hi>dear to Chriſt,</hi> and ought to be ſo to each other! Do we not ſee how in <hi>Stormy Times,</hi> the poor Sheep and other Cattel will <hi>run together;</hi> how they get into their <hi>Folds</hi> and <hi>Flocks;</hi> how they herd themſelves with a kind of <hi>united force;</hi> eſpecially when the <hi>worrying Dogs</hi> and <hi>Wolves</hi> are abroad; do they not all then haſten to their <hi>Shelters</hi> and their <hi>Shepherds?</hi> And ſhall the very <hi>Inſtinct</hi> of Nature teach the <hi>Brute Beaſts</hi> by this their <hi>mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion</hi> to defend themſelves againſt preſent miſchiefs, or approach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing dangers, and ſhall not the moſt <hi>Noble Principle</hi> of <hi>Grace,</hi> called in the Scripture, the <hi>Wiſdom from on high,</hi> much more teach men (good men!) to do the like? What is it would or could more <hi>diſanimate</hi> the very worſt and moſt potent Enemies the <hi>truly Reformed Proteſtant Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion</hi> hath, than to ſee the ſeveral <hi>diſſenting Parties</hi> of ſound Proteſtants, firmly to unite together, and by mutual <hi>Allowances</hi> in the few things wherein they differ, to ſtrengthen each other in the <hi>maintenance of the Faith which they have received</hi> from Chriſt and his Apoſtles, and do on all hands think it their higheſt concernment to profeſs and bear teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny unto? This therefore may well challenge the firſt place in the Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods humbly offered for reſtoring the aforeſaid <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> to a <hi>flouriſhing ſtate.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> An <hi>univerſal, conſtant</hi> and <hi>conſcientious care</hi> and endeavour in all <hi>Proteſtant Families</hi> throughout theſe Three Kingdoms, diligently to <hi>inſtruct</hi> their Children and Servants in the <hi>ſound Principles</hi> of the ſaid truly <hi>Reformed Proteſtant Religion:</hi> The like care to be uſed by all
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:52086:5"/>
               <hi>Schoolmaſters, Tutors, Guardians,</hi> and others that have any charge of Souls under them; but moſt of all by <hi>Preaching Miniſters,</hi> where-ever opportunity for ſuch Work can be had. For the better accompliſhment whereof, care is to be taken that <hi>ſuch Catechiſms</hi> may be made uſe of, as have no <hi>mixtures of Error</hi> in them, or are in any thing <hi>contrary to,</hi> or <hi>not agreeing with</hi> the <hi>Holy Scriptures;</hi> particularly in the Doctrine of the <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath;</hi> and the <hi>Morality</hi> thereof; in which <hi>Calvin</hi> him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf (though otherwiſe a very famous and ſound Divine) was <hi>defective.</hi> The Miſtake of whoſe opinion therein, hath had too much influence upon the <hi>Proteſtant Churches</hi> abroad) moſt of all in <hi>France</hi> and the ſeven <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Provinces</hi>) as to the <hi>looſeneſs</hi> of their Lives and whole Chriſtian Profeſſion. And here without offence let it be enquired, whether the ſtrict obſervation of the <hi>Chrrſtian Sabbath,</hi> as a <hi>Divine Inſtitution</hi> of Chriſt, here in <hi>England,</hi> hath not rendred the <hi>ſincere Profeſſors</hi> of this Nation <hi>more eminent</hi> in all practical holineſs than others of <hi>Foreign Parts?</hi> A firm belief of the Morality of our <hi>Lords-Day-Rest,</hi> and a due obſervation of it accordingly, contains no ſmall part of the very <hi>Power of Godlineſs</hi> in it, as well as the Form thereof. The truth is, the careful and reverent regard unto this Day, as well in mens <hi>ſecret Cloſets</hi> and <hi>private Families,</hi> as in <hi>Publick Aſſemblies,</hi> hath kept up a <hi>pure</hi> and <hi>warm Religion</hi> more in <hi>England</hi> than in any part of the world beſides. Even to this day, who do we find to be the moſt <hi>ſavoury</hi> and <hi>ſpiritual</hi> in Diſcourſe, the moſt <hi>exemplary</hi> and worthy of imitation in <hi>their Lives,</hi> but thoſe that are moſt <hi>ſtrict</hi> in an holy obſervation of <hi>this Day? That have turned away their feet from the Sabbath</hi> (as the Lord ſpeaks by the Prophet, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 58.13.) <hi>from doing their pleaſure on his holy day, and have called the Sabbath a delight, the holy of the Lord, honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, and have honoured him, not doing their own wayes, nor finding their own pleaſure, nor ſpeaking their own words:</hi> I ſay, who ſo much as theſe doth God himſelf delight in, and all good men?</p>
            <p>But if any ſay, that this concerns the <hi>Jews</hi> only, and thoſe that keep the <hi>Seventh-day-Sabbath;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I anſwer, If thoſe that are of that mind will but take pains to read what Biſhop <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> in his <hi>Sum and Subſtance of Chriſtian-Religion,</hi> hath written upon the tranſlation of the Sabbath or time of reſt, from the <hi>Seventh day</hi> to the <hi>Firſt day</hi> of the Week, with the Reaſons of it; as alſo what is publiſhed upon this Subject, not only formerly by many Learned Writers, but alſo of late by Mr. <hi>Hughes</hi> of <hi>Plimouth,</hi> Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> Mr. <hi>Wells,</hi> and others; but eſpecially that moſt excellent Treatiſe upon it lately Printed, with this Title, <hi>Exercitations concerning the
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:52086:5"/>
Name, Original, Nature, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe and Continuance of a day of Sacred Reſt; together with an Aſſertion of the Divine inſtitution of the Lord's Day, and Practical Directions for its due Obſervation.</hi> I ſay, whoſoever will pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure, and take pains to read over theſe Books, will ſoon find <hi>ſufficient reaſon</hi> to believe, that the aforeſaid words of the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cerning the Sabbath, are <hi>very aptly applicable</hi> to the due Obſervers of our <hi>Chriſtian Sabbath.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now of all the ſpiritual employments of this Day, next to an at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendance upon Publick Ordinances, in the <hi>Solemn Aſſemblies</hi> of the Saints; what hath been ever found to be more profitable, than when the Heads of Families, and others in their reſpective capacities, have by <hi>Queſtions and Anſwers</hi> in a <hi>Catechetical way,</hi> conveyed the <hi>ſound knowledge</hi> of Chriſt and his great Goſpel-Truths into the hearts of thoſe committed to their care? <hi>Reading</hi> the Holy Scriptures alſo, <hi>repeating</hi> Sermons, <hi>ſinging of Pſalms,</hi> and calling upon God in fervent Prayer, are all <hi>Sabbath-day</hi> Exerciſes in a Family: And <hi>bleſſed</hi> are thoſe Fami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lies that are alwayes ſo employed. But the doing of this in an <hi>Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>locutory way,</hi> with Children and Servants, ſo as to make them <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand</hi> what they hear and read, and be enriched with the well-grounded knowledge of it; <hi>O this is excellent!</hi> and one of the beſt means imagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable to preſerve the <hi>True Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and to tranſmit it from Father to Son, even from one Generation to another. And becauſe a clear and diſtinct knowledge of <hi>Fundamental and Subſtantial</hi> Truths, with ſuch Texts of Scripture as do moſt contribute to the right under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, confirmation and defence of them againſt all oppoſers what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, will be a moſt precious Antidote, as well againſt all ſorts of Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="4 letters">
                  <desc>••••</desc>
               </gap> as thoſe of <hi>Popery</hi> it ſelf, I humbly propound to the pious Readers hereof theſe following Conſiderations.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> Let it be conſidered, whether it would not be time well ſpent, if ſome perſons of <hi>Wiſdom</hi> and <hi>Ability,</hi> whether engaged in any Church-Society, or otherwiſe, were appointed (or themſelves did it by their own <hi>voluntary</hi> undertakement) to go <hi>from houſe to houſe</hi> at fit times and ſeaſons, there to diſcourſe the <hi>weighty things</hi> of Religion with their Friends and Neighbours, and ſo to manage this Work, as ſtill to leave the perſons they thus converſe with ſomething <hi>more knowing</hi> in the great things of Religion than formerly? Frequent Viſits to this pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, with <hi>Line upon Line, here a little and there a little,</hi> would turn to a much better account both with reſpect to <hi>God's Glory,</hi> the advance<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of <hi>Chriſt's Kingdom</hi> in the world, and the enlightning of many precious ſouls with <hi>ſaving knowledge,</hi> than ſuch vain Viſits as are every
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:52086:6"/>
where now in uſe. In ſome places, the Paſtors and other Officers of the Churches may do <hi>ſomething</hi> this way themſelves, after the example of that holy Perſon, and worthy Servant of Chriſt, Mr. <hi>Henry Jeſſe,</hi> lately deceaſed; but where the hands of <hi>Church-Officers</hi> are full of other work, perhaps ſome others in their reſpective Congregations might be found and prevailed with, to do their utmoſt in it; at leaſt, ſo far as might conſiſt with their neceſſary employments in their reſpective trades and callings. This is <hi>brave work,</hi> and doubtleſs will be well reward<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the God of Heaven, to the faithful and ſincere-hearted <hi>Labourers</hi> in it. What doth the <hi>gracious</hi> and <hi>induſtrious Parent</hi> know, but that his continual dropping of heavenly words into his <hi>Children's</hi> ears; or the religious and loving Friend or Neighbour that doth the like with all that he converſeth with (where a fair oportunity is offered) may be a means to work ſome bleſſed <hi>Conviction;</hi> yea, and a through <hi>Converſion</hi> too, in the hearts of thoſe they thus diſcourſe with? Chriſt may be preached as much and as <hi>effectually</hi> in <hi>perſonal</hi> and <hi>interlocutory diſcourſes,</hi> as in ſet ſpeeches, or <hi>Sermons in a Pulpit;</hi> nay, I know many inſtances can be given, where Diſcourſes of this kind have done <hi>more this way,</hi> than all the Sermons that have been attended, though preached by men of the <hi>greateſt eminency,</hi> for many years; as the Apoſtle ſayes in another caſe, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7.16 <hi>What knoweſt thou, O Wife, whether thou ſhalt ſave thy Husband? or how knoweſt thou, O man, whether thou ſhalt ſave thy Wife?</hi> So ſay I; What knoweſt thou, <hi>O Parent,</hi> whether thou ſhalt ſave thy <hi>Child?</hi> or what knoweſt thou, <hi>O Chriſtian,</hi> whether thou ſhalt ſave thy <hi>Friend</hi> or <hi>Neighbour,</hi> thy <hi>Brother</hi> or <hi>Siſter</hi> by ſuch ſpiritual and well ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>naged Diſcourſes as theſe? However, if it be but <hi>well deſigned and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavoured,</hi> God takes it well, though the deſired effect ſhould not fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low. Methinks that Paſſage in <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3 ſhould greatly move to ſuch an undertakement and earneſt endeavour therein; <hi>They that be wiſe</hi> (in the Margin, <hi>Teachers) ſhall ſhine as the brightneſs of the firmament, and they that turn many to righteouſneſs, as the Stars for ever and ever.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> Let it be conſidered whether of all other, ſuch as are <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents of Children</hi> ought not to be frequent at ſuch work as this. I mean, not only upon <hi>Sabbath Dayes</hi> and other <hi>Set Seaſons</hi> for Religious Exer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſes, but in their <hi>daily</hi> and <hi>hourly</hi> converſe among them; for is not this according to the Command of <hi>old</hi> given to the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as a work that their <hi>whole heart</hi> and <hi>ſoul</hi> ſhould be continually engaged in? What God required of them in this particular, is it not recorded for our inſtruction, in <hi>Deut.</hi> 6. from <hi>v.</hi> 4, to 7? <hi>Hear, O Iſrael, thou ſhalt love the Lord thy God with all thy ſoul, and with all thy might; and theſe
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:52086:6"/>
words which I command thee this day, ſhall be in thy heart, and thou ſhalt teach them diligently (Hebrew,</hi> thou ſhalt whet or ſharpen them) <hi>unto thy Children, and ſhalt talk of them when thou ſitteſt in thy houſe, and when thou walkeſt in the way, and when thou lieſt down, and when thou riſeſt up.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now if this be a Command that is alwayes <hi>obliging,</hi> and to <hi>all Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> whatſoever (as doubtleſs it is) what then can we, in a well-grounded Charity, think of <hi>thoſe</hi> Parents and Profeſſors of Religion too, that order their affairs ſo, as <hi>very ſeldom,</hi> even <hi>almoſt next to never at all,</hi> are with their Children either Morning or Evening, much leſs all the day long, to perform theſe, ſo frequently to be repeated duties to them? Such <hi>hurries</hi> they are in, ſuch <hi>multitudes of buſineſs</hi> and <hi>employments</hi> they continually take upon them; yea, ſo <hi>fill</hi> and <hi>crowd</hi> their heads and hearts therewith, that they neither have any <hi>mind,</hi> nor can be at <hi>leiſure</hi> for theſe <hi>ſerious matters.</hi> Pretences indeed they make, of being commanded to be <hi>diligent</hi> in their Callings, and of a <hi>neceſſity</hi> lying on them with reſpect to providing for their Families, and ſuch like <hi>ſpecious Arguments</hi> from <hi>abuſed Scriptures;</hi> but whether theſe Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments will <hi>quiet Conſcience</hi> upon a dying Bed, I very much queſtion; I know the care of providing for the Houſhold, lies <hi>moſtly</hi> upon the man, who is the Husband to the Wife, and the Father to the Children; and that it is the <hi>Mother's</hi> Duty, as well as the <hi>Father's</hi> to inſtruct the Children, and to <hi>bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord;</hi> but will this excuſe the Father from doing his part too? or will it ſatisfie him in <hi>clogging himſelf</hi> with ſo much other employment, and that in ſuch an eager purſuit after the things of this world only, as ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>hinders</hi> him in the performance of it, or renders him <hi>unfit</hi> for it? As for his poor Children and Family thus neglected by him, is not the inſtructing them in the <hi>One thing neceſſary,</hi> and the <hi>ſaving of their preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſouls,</hi> of <hi>far greater importance,</hi> than the getting of overmuch of this world for them?</p>
            <p>But if this be not enough, eſpecially in ſuch times as theſe, when the true <hi>Protestant Religion</hi> is ſo much in its <hi>wane,</hi> and <hi>Popery</hi> every where <hi>ſpreads ſo faſt</hi> as it doth: I ſay, if this be not enough to <hi>convince</hi> and <hi>reform</hi> ſuch Fathers of Children, as to this part of their Duty, I ſhall leave them to, and pity them for this their <hi>Sin</hi> and <hi>Folly;</hi> and in the mean while, will apply my ſelf to the <hi>Mothers</hi> of thoſe poor <hi>neglected Children,</hi> earneſtly adviſing and perſwading, that what is wanting on the Father's ſide, may be made up by them; and indeed, the <hi>Mothers</hi> of Children for the moſt part, have every where <hi>more opportunity</hi> for
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:52086:7"/>
this work, as being more conſtantly at home and w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="5 letters">
                  <desc>•••••</desc>
               </gap>oors, and to <hi>converſe more with their Children</hi> than their Fathers can. They there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, if God gives wiſdom and skill to educate the Children which they have <hi>brought forth,</hi> or as Mothers-in-Law, are <hi>providentially intruſted</hi> with, may be much employed this way, and with the bleſſing of God upon their faithful endeavours herein, may become Mothers <hi>a ſecond time</hi> unto them, in their ſpiritual Births: I have known ſome women that have been much honoured of God for their <hi>Holy Labours</hi> and <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Succeſſes</hi> of this kind, among their <hi>Children</hi> and their <hi>Childrens Children;</hi> and this, while their Husbands have been meer <hi>Sots;</hi> yea, ſometimes Oppoſers and <hi>Hinderers</hi> of it. Inſtances we have in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture alſo that may greatly encourage unto this work. How came young <hi>Timothy</hi> to be ſo well inſtructed as (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>) from his <hi>Childhood</hi> or <hi>Infancy,</hi> as the Greek word imports, <hi>to have known the Holy Scriptures?</hi> 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3.15. I ſay, how came this to paſs, but by the Godly and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious care and endeavours of thoſe two holy women, his <hi>Grandmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Lois, and his Mother Eunice?</hi> as is recorded, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.5.</p>
            <p>What a pleaſant Story doth <hi>Solomon</hi> tell us of himſelf, concerning his <hi>own education,</hi> when he was <hi>young?</hi> See what he ſayes of the In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructions which he received both from his <hi>Father</hi> and his <hi>Mother.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> From his <hi>Father,</hi> whoſe words he repeats throughout the whole fourth Chap. of <hi>Prov.</hi> ſome of which are theſe; <hi>Hear ye Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren the inſtruction of a Father, and attend to know underſtanding; for I give you good Doctrine; forſake you not my Law; for I was my Father's ſon, tender and only beloved in the ſight of my Mother; he taught me alſo, and ſaid unto me, let thine heart retain my words, keep my Commandments and live; get wiſdom, get underſtanding, forget it not, neither decline from the words of my mouth; forſake her not, and ſhe ſhall preſerve thee: love her, and ſhe ſhall keep thee; wiſdom is the principal thing, therefore get wiſdom, and with all thy getting, get underſtanding; exalt her, and ſhe ſhall promote thee; ſhe ſhall bring thee to honour when thou dost embrace her: She ſhall give to thine head an Ornament of Grace, a Crown of Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſhall ſhe deliver to thee. Hear, O my Son, and receive my Sayings, and the years of thy Life ſhall be many. I have taught thee in the way of wiſdom, I have led thee in the right paths; when thou goeſt, thy ſteps ſhall not be ſtreightned, and when thou runneſt, thou ſhalt not ſtumble; take faſt hold of Inſtruction, let her not go, keep her, for ſhe is thy Life.</hi> Theſe and many other, were the moſt <hi>excellent</hi> counſels to the end of the whole Chapter, which <hi>Solomon</hi> ſayes his <hi>Father</hi> gave him: in all which, how <hi>earneſt</hi> and <hi>affectionate</hi> was <hi>David</hi> in preſſing thoſe things upon his
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:52086:7"/>
Son <hi>Solomon;</hi> and how many Arguments doth he uſe to perſwade him thereunto? But that which all <hi>Fathers of Children</hi> ſhould do well here chiefly to mind, is, the <hi>chief Matter</hi> of that Inſtruction which <hi>David</hi> gives to his Son <hi>Solomon;</hi> namely, that he ſhould <hi>get wiſdom</hi> (that is, Grace) for ſo the word muſt be underſtood; and that he ſhould be ſure <hi>to get this above all things elſe,</hi> even above all other gettings whatſoever; and he gives the reaſon of it; for this, ſaith he, is the <hi>principal thing:</hi> as if he had ſaid, this, O my Son <hi>Solomon,</hi> is of far <hi>greater worth</hi> and <hi>value</hi> than the <hi>Kingdom</hi> and <hi>Crown</hi> that thou art born unto; the <hi>Scep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter</hi> that thou ſhalt ere long ſway, and the <hi>Throne</hi> that thou ſhalt fit up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; more excellent, far more, than all the Kingly Dignity and Honour that thou art capable of, or canſt enjoy in this world.</p>
            <p>Hence it was, that <hi>Solomon</hi> himſelf, having learnt this Leſſon from his Father, ſets it forth in that manner that he doth, in <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. from <hi>v.</hi> 13. to 19. <hi>Happy is the man</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that findeth wiſdom, and the man that getteth underſtanding; for the Merchandiſe of it is better than the Merchandiſe of Silver, and the gain thereof than fine Gold; ſhe is more precious than Rubies, and all the things thou canst deſire are not to be com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared unto her.</hi> Thus he goes on, <hi>ſaying</hi> much more concerning the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſtimable value of that wiſdom which his Father taught him to ſearch after, and which himſelf afterwards ſo <hi>earneſtly prayed for</hi> at his firſt coming to his Kingdom; as is recorded in 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 3. from 6. to 13.</p>
            <p>And as we have this pleaſant Story from <hi>Solomon's</hi> own mouth, of his <hi>Father's inſtructing</hi> him when he was young, let us ſee what he ſayes of his <hi>Mother's</hi> Inſtruction alſo, his Mother <hi>Bathſhebah;</hi> as it is like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe recorded in <hi>Prov.</hi> 31. from 1, to 10. <hi>The words of King Lemuel</hi> (that is, <hi>Solomon) the Prophecy that his Mother taught him, What, my Son! and what the Son of my womb! and what the Son of my Vows! Give not thy ſtrength unto women, nor thy wayes to that which deſtroyeth Kings: It is not for Kings, O Lemuel, it is not for Kings to drink wine, nor for Princes ſtrong Drink, leſt they drink and forget the Law, and pervert the judgment of any of the afflicted. Open thy mouth for the dumb, in the cauſe of all ſuch as are appointed to deſtruction; open thy mouth to judge righteouſly and plead the cauſe of the poor and needy.</hi> Behold here the counſel of a <hi>Mother</hi> to her <hi>Son,</hi> of a <hi>Queen-Mother</hi> to the <hi>King her Son:</hi> how happy were it if all the Kings of the Earth were thus in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and did act accordingly?</p>
            <p n="3">3ly, Since the H. Ghoſt inſiſteth ſo much upon the <hi>inſtruction of young ones,</hi> ſince he gives ſo ſtrict commands to Parents concerning it, and to others that are in the room of Parents; and ſince he commendeth and
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:52086:8"/>
bleſſeth thoſe that have been <hi>faithful</hi> in the diſcharge of this ſo neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and great a Duty; as he did <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gen. 18.19. <hi>Saying, Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham ſhall ſurely become a great and a mighty Nation, and all the Nations of the Earth ſhall be bleſſed in him.</hi> Why ſo? <hi>For I know</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>that he will command his Children and his Houſhold after him; and they ſhall keep the way of the Lord to do juſtice and judgment.</hi> I ſay, this alſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing duly conſidered, would it not be an excellent and <hi>praiſe-worthy</hi> pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice, if <hi>young perſons</hi> of their own accord, <hi>Males with Males, and Fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>males with Females,</hi> would every where, all <hi>England</hi> over (as in ſome places I know they do) meet together, and that not only to pray with each other, and repeat Sermons (a practice very commendable and profitable) but alſo to confer together upon the <hi>Fundamentals of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion,</hi> which they have read and learned out of ſome well-approved Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>techiſm, with the Scriptures alledged for the proofs of them. Many of theſe, eſpecially, <hi>if under the age of ſixteen years,</hi> may meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther for ſuch religious purpoſes, and be no <hi>Conventiclers.</hi> What pity is it then that ſuch Meetings of <hi>young ones</hi> are not every where in uſe, for mutual edification and inſtructions, which that they might thrive the better, would not ſome one <hi>grave perſon</hi> among them, to guide and aſſiſt them therein, very much <hi>help</hi> them in ſuch a pious work?</p>
            <p>Were this and the like endeavours by Parents and others, as afore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaid, every where in common practice, what <hi>bleſſed advantages</hi> would from thence ariſe as to the propagating of the truly Reformed <hi>Proteſtant Religion?</hi> Among which, would not this be one great one, above the reſt, namely, the <hi>facilitating</hi> the work of the publick Miniſtry, both as to <hi>Conviction, Converſion</hi> and <hi>Edification</hi> too, whilſt the reſpective Auditories up and down the Kingdom would be, as it were, <hi>all beſpang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led</hi> and <hi>richly enamell'd</hi> with well-inſtructed Families, and piouſly af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected Auditors? What <hi>tractable, attentive</hi> and <hi>underſtanding</hi> Hearers would the Congregations be repleniſhed withal? What <hi>flouriſhing ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects,</hi> what <hi>pleaſant fruits</hi> would the Labourers in Chriſt's Vineyards find their faithful Labours to be <hi>crowned withal?</hi> Sure, if any way can poſſibly be thought of not only to <hi>preſerve</hi> and <hi>reſtore</hi> the true <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant Religion,</hi> but to put it into a <hi>more proſperous eſtate</hi> than ever it was known to be in in this Kingdom before; <hi>this is it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>But though what hath been ſaid hitherto, may through the bleſſing of God, if put in practice, prove good and effectual means to <hi>raiſe</hi> and <hi>revive,</hi> as it were, the <hi>truly Reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> from the preſent <hi>ſwooning</hi> and almoſt <hi>dying</hi> ſtate in which it ſeems every where to be; yet there is another thing no leſs important, to be moſt <hi>intenſely</hi>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:52086:8"/>
minded and laid to heart by all <hi>conſiderate</hi> and <hi>ſound Proteſtants,</hi> and that is, what is like to become of the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> a few years hence, if no better courſe be taken for the continuance and ſupport of it, than is any where now on foot?</p>
            <p>As for <hi>Popery,</hi> that is kept up and maintained, not only by the <hi>Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> and <hi>Potentates</hi> of moſt Parts of <hi>Chriſtendom,</hi> but by a continued <hi>nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merous ſucceſſion</hi> of Learned (though miſerably blinded) men; as Chriſt ſayes in another caſe, the men of that <hi>dark Antichriſtian Kingdom are wiſer in their generation than the Children of Light;</hi> they are careful, from Age to Age, to find out and ſet apart the very <hi>Flower</hi> of their <hi>Youth,</hi> the moſt <hi>pregnant, fine-witted Lads</hi> that they can any where meet with throughout their <hi>Popiſh Kingdoms;</hi> upon theſe they ſpare no coſt nor pains, to educate and bring them up in the <hi>profoundeſt Learning</hi> and <hi>largeſt improvement</hi> of their Parts, according to their reſpective <hi>Genius</hi>'s and inclinations, to become ſerviceable in the propagation and defence of their <hi>falſe Religion.</hi> But alas! how little of this (in compariſon) is done by the <hi>Proteſtant</hi> Party <hi>all</hi> Europe <hi>over?</hi> Inſomuch that if God in his good providence doth not ſome way prevent it, and provide a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it, the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> ere long is not like to have many men of Parts and Learning able to defend it againſt its <hi>ſubtil</hi> and <hi>inveterate Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſary</hi> the Church of <hi>Rome:</hi> And how doth this <hi>glad</hi> the <hi>Romiſh</hi> Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick at the very heart, and fill him with <hi>hopes,</hi> that in the next ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration he ſhall <hi>carry all</hi> before him, and that, how zealous and ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsful ſoever ſome may now be, in <hi>preaching, writing</hi> and <hi>diſputing</hi> againſt them; yet that the Children of them that do ſo, will be other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe <hi>minded,</hi> or at leaſt, through <hi>Ignorance</hi> and want of Learning, will not be able to maintain the <hi>noble and righteous Cauſe,</hi> which their Forefathers did, and that <hi>irrefragably</hi> and <hi>invincibly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now therefore ſince the caſe is thus, <hi>O all you zealous, true-hearted, and ſound Proteſtants throughout theſe Kingdoms of</hi> England, Scotland, <hi>and</hi> Ireland, let me humbly propound an <hi>Expedient</hi> to you, that hath been upon my heart for ſome years; an Expedient, which I conceive is as <hi>feaſible</hi> as <hi>obvious,</hi> if God give men hearts readily to <hi>comply</hi> with what I ſhall here ſuggeſt concerning it; which if they ſhall every where <hi>unanimouſly</hi> and <hi>vigorouſly</hi> ſet then ſelves about, I ſhall no way doubt, but that within the ſpace of <hi>fifteen or twenty years,</hi> the truly Reformed <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> ſhall have no want of ſuch as in due time, through the Bleſſing of God, ſhall become the <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>unconquerable Defend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> of it againſt the greateſt Champions the <hi>Church of Rome</hi> ſhall be able to produce.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="12" facs="tcp:52086:9"/>Now that which in order hereunto I have to propound, will briefly fall under two Propoſitions.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That aſſoon as may be, all the Children of ſuch true-hearted and Religious Proteſtants as are ſcattered up &amp; down in the three King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms and the ſeveral Schools in them, whether publick or private, and ſhall be found of pregnant parts, and well-grounded in <hi>Grammar</hi>-learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, be ſpeedily committed to ſuch Pious, Orthodox and Learned men as ſhall be found able and willing to inſtruct and educate them in <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſity-Studies,</hi> and eſpecially in thoſe <hi>Languages, Arts</hi> and <hi>Sciences</hi> as may render them <hi>able Diſputants</hi> and <hi>good Divines.</hi> I confine my ſelf to the Children only of <hi>true-hearted</hi> and <hi>Religious Proteſtants,</hi> becauſe I preſume no others will make their Children ſo happy as to be ſo bred up.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That from time to time, all true-<hi>hearted</hi> and <hi>Religious Proteſtants,</hi> as aforeſaid (whether rich or poor) will ſet apart <hi>ſuch of their Children</hi> as they ſhall find <hi>moſt eminent</hi> and <hi>hopeful</hi> for <hi>natural Parts, Capacities</hi> and <hi>Diſpoſitions,</hi> unto this great ſervice of the Goſpel; and as they grow up, to ſend them to the <hi>Grammar-Schools;</hi> and ſo to high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Studies. Several Objections, perhaps, may here come in againſt theſe two Propoſitions; one from the <hi>rich Proteſtants,</hi> the other from the <hi>poor.</hi> From the rich: We have Eſtates to give our Children, ſay they, and thereupon intend ſome of them for the <hi>Inns of Court,</hi> and from thence, for higher <hi>employments;</hi> others we intend for <hi>Merchants,</hi> or ſuch and ſuch <hi>gainful Trades;</hi> for what encouragement is there to bring them up to that ſort of Learning which may fit them for Services in the Church, when they are not like to <hi>get any preferment</hi> or employ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment without ſuch <hi>ſinful Compliances</hi> and time-ſerving <hi>Conformities,</hi> both in Doctrines and Manners, as may <hi>corrupt</hi> their Hearts, <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bauch</hi> their Conſciences, and endanger their Souls for ever?</p>
            <p>To theſe I anſwer; <hi>Firſt,</hi> To thoſe that deſign their Children to <hi>high employments,</hi> in caſe they bring them up to the aforeſaid <hi>great</hi> Service of the Goſpel, and (as <hi>Hannah</hi> did her Son <hi>Samuel) conſecrate</hi> them to the Lord, and to his <hi>Temple-work,</hi> I conceive, they thereby advance them to <hi>no mean</hi> employment; but rather to as <hi>noble</hi> an one as any that can be named; it is no deſpicable work in the Apoſtles ſence, <hi>to ſerve at the Altar,</hi> nor was it ſo in God's own account, when <hi>he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified his Son Jeſus to be a Prieſt,</hi> Heb. 5.4, 5. <hi>Solomon</hi> was the <hi>greateſt</hi> and the <hi>wiſest</hi> King that ever the world had, and yet was a <hi>Preacher;</hi> ſo was <hi>David</hi> his Father, before him, a <hi>Preacher</hi> and a <hi>Prophet,</hi> Pſal. 40.
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:52086:9"/>
9, 10. So alſo were the <hi>Princes</hi> of <hi>Jehoſhaphat;</hi> of whom it is ſaid, that <hi>they taught the People in the Cities of Judah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And for thoſe that ſay they have <hi>Eſtates</hi> to give to theſe their Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, by which they may be able to live without other preferments, eſpecially thoſe which come in by <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Employments;</hi> Well, ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mit it be ſo, will they not ſhew <hi>their love</hi> to Chriſt ſo much the more, in dedicating their <hi>Children</hi> and their <hi>Eſtates too,</hi> unto his Service? eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially in ſuch an Age as this, when the <hi>right ſort of Proteſtants</hi> every where, for the moſt part, are <hi>ſo poor,</hi> that they cannot give ſo <hi>li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beral a maintenance</hi> to the painful Preachers of the Goſpel, as they deſire and gladly would if they were able; and in caſe they bring up their Children to <hi>Idleneſs,</hi> becauſe they have Eſtates to leave to them, and ſo put them into <hi>no Calling</hi> or <hi>Employment</hi> at all, what do they thereby do, but render them in a manner <hi>wholly uſeleſs</hi> both to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>State?</hi> and which is worſe, <hi>expoſe</hi> them to all manner of <hi>Temptations</hi> and <hi>Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> which are wont to accompany an <hi>idle</hi> courſe of Life: and what <hi>comfort</hi> can <hi>Parents</hi> have in this, or their <hi>Children</hi> either? or what <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts</hi> will they both give hereof at the laſt day?</p>
            <p>For thoſe that differ from both the former, that is, neither intend their Children for high employments, nor yet to leave them Eſtates without Callings, but deſign them for <hi>Merchandizing</hi> and other <hi>gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Trades,</hi> becauſe they ſee no hopes of <hi>Eccleſiaſtical preferments,</hi> but upon the ill terms before mentioned. I ſhall only ſay thus much to them, if <hi>one great cauſe</hi> of the future decay of the <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> ſhould be the want of ſuch able men to defend it, as their Children in all probability might have proved to have been, had they been, in <hi>pure love to Chriſt</hi> and his Truth, <hi>dedicated</hi> and <hi>brought up thereunto;</hi> and ſo by that means, as much, if not more than any other, <hi>Popery</hi> ſhould over-run this Land, what good will their gainful Trades do them in ſuch a <hi>diſmal change?</hi> and how little will God and their Country be beholding to them for this their <hi>carnal policy</hi> and <hi>eager purſuit</hi> after worldly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantages, with the loſs of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> and the <hi>True Religion</hi> which it holds forth?</p>
            <p>To that which is ſaid concerning the want of <hi>encouragement</hi> from <hi>Eccleſiastical preferments;</hi> if Chriſt himſelf be <hi>worthy</hi> of <hi>credit,</hi> and may be <hi>believed</hi> in what he ſayes, ſuch as go forth in his Name, to preach the everlaſting Goſpel, ſhall not want <hi>ſubſistance nor encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> in that work; but ſhall be ſure where they come, to <hi>find welcom</hi> as well for their <hi>Perſons,</hi> as their <hi>Doctrine;</hi> and ſhall not need to take care either <hi>for ſcrips for their journey, or for two coats, or for ſhoes,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:52086:10"/>
or for ſtaves, no, nor for Gold or Silver, or Braſs in their Purſes,</hi> Matth. 10.9, 10.</p>
            <p>Let this then ſuffice for anſwer to the Objections of the <hi>rich Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Now for thoſe of the <hi>Poor;</hi> they alſo do make two Objections; one is, that they are totally unable to <hi>maintain</hi> their Children, or to bring them up in Learning, either in <hi>Schools</hi> or <hi>Academies,</hi> they have not where withal to do it. The other is, they are neceſſitated to train them up in ſome way even ſo ſoon as ever capable to get their <hi>own living,</hi> if not to be <hi>helpful</hi> to them their poor <hi>Parents</hi> alſo, and ſo cannot ſpare or allow them time for <hi>ſuch education</hi> as aforeſaid: were we able, ſay they, we would do it moſt <hi>willingly;</hi> but we cannot.</p>
            <p>Now for the removal of this difficulty, I would become an <hi>humble</hi> and <hi>earneſt petitioner</hi> to ſeveral ſorts of <hi>Rich Proteſtants</hi> in theſe King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doms.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> To all <hi>rich Proteſtants</hi> both <hi>Males</hi> and <hi>Females,</hi> that, though <hi>rich,</hi> yet by the Providence of God, ſome way or other, are <hi>determin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to a ſingle life,</hi> and have power to <hi>diſpoſe</hi> of their Eſtates as ſeemeth good unto themſelves.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> To all ſuch rich Proteſtants in the married ſtate, that have <hi>no Iſſue</hi> or Kindred to provide for, or at leaſt, ſuch as have <hi>no need</hi> of them.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> To all ſuch <hi>rich Proteſtants,</hi> as, though bleſſed with Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, and may have other Relations to take care of; yet have ſo <hi>plenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful an Eſtate,</hi> that when all are well provided for, enough remains for other acts of <hi>Piety</hi> and <hi>Charity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Fourthly,</hi> To all ſuch <hi>rich Proteſtants</hi> as have <hi>purpoſes</hi> in their own hearts to diſpoſe of the whole or any part of their Eſtates to ſome <hi>good uſe</hi> or other, but are not yet determined which way to do it, but would be glad to be <hi>adviſed</hi> how to improve what they have, ſo as <hi>God</hi> may be moſt <hi>glorified,</hi> and the <hi>publick good advanced</hi> in the Places and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries where they live.</p>
            <p>To theſe four ſorts of <hi>rich Proteſtants</hi> I will now addreſs my ſelf, and among other acts of <hi>Piety</hi> which they may have thoughts of, would earneſtly perſwade to theſe which follow.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That ſuch <hi>pregnant Youths</hi> as are above-deſcribed, who either have <hi>no parents</hi> alive, but are poor diſtreſſed <hi>Orphans,</hi> and in a manner altogether <hi>friendleſs,</hi> or are the Children of poor <hi>Widows,</hi> poor <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conforming Miniſters,</hi> or other poor Proteſtants fearing God, may be adopted or taken care of by them, in <hi>Grammar Schools</hi> and <hi>Academies,</hi>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:52086:10"/>
for the ends aforeſaid; and that in order hereunto, <hi>Feoffees</hi> in truſt may be appointed (good and faithful men) to ſeek out for <hi>ſuch</hi> as thoſe, and to place them in <hi>good Schools</hi> and <hi>Academies,</hi> under ſuch <hi>Maſters</hi> and <hi>Tutors</hi> as ſhall be found moſt <hi>able</hi> and <hi>faithful</hi> in inſtructing ſuch as ſhall be ſo committed to their care, in Learning and Piety; with this limitation, that in caſe any of the ſaid Youths grow <hi>debauched,</hi> or within the compaſs of the times prefixed for them to be provided for, do fall into any <hi>erroneous Opinions</hi> or evil practices contrary or preju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicial to the <hi>true Reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> they ſhall thenceforth be caſhiered, and enjoy no further benefit of the ſaid <hi>Mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As for their <hi>Academical Studies</hi> after they leave the Grammar-Schools, I propound <hi>ten</hi> or <hi>twelve</hi> years at leaſt to be ſpent in them; for this main reaſon, that they may have <hi>ſpace ſufficient,</hi> before they enter into the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> to lay a good foundation of <hi>ſolid Learning,</hi> and be the more ripened in their <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Abilities</hi> both Natural and Acquired, for ſo great a work as a <hi>right Preaching</hi> of the Goſpel is; for if they be of <hi>pregnant Wits,</hi> and <hi>good Sudents,</hi> they may within the ſpace of the ſaid <hi>ten</hi> or <hi>twelve</hi> years, be competently well acquaint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with the <hi>Learned Languages</hi> and all thoſe <hi>Liberal Sciences,</hi> the knowledge whereof is requiſite to the ſtudy of <hi>Divinity;</hi> and in all which by daily ſtudy and practice, they will ſtill become more and more <hi>expert,</hi> in which chief part of their ſtudies, I mean <hi>Divinity,</hi> I conceive it would not be amiſs, if they were <hi>particularly obliged</hi> by their <hi>Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>factors,</hi> to read ſuch of the <hi>ſoundest</hi> and moſt <hi>ancient</hi> Fathers and <hi>best Schoolmen</hi> as comply moſt with the Doctrine of true <hi>Reformed Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantiſm;</hi> as alſo, that they be further obliged to read ſuch of the <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dern Writers,</hi> both <hi>German</hi> and <hi>French,</hi> as are likewiſe of the ſame <hi>Judgment,</hi> but eſpeciallly, that they be much verſed in our <hi>Engliſh Divines</hi> not touched with <hi>Arminianiſm</hi> or other the like Errors; ſuch ſuch as <hi>Jewel,</hi> both the <hi>Reynolds's, Perkins, Ameſius, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſher,</hi> with the worthy Labours of <hi>Preſton, Sibs,</hi> Mr. <hi>Anthony Burges, Burroughs, Bridge,</hi> Mr. <hi>Iſaac Ambroſe, Allen, Owen, Greenhill,</hi> Mr. <hi>Sydrach Symp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Symonds, Spurſtow, Sedgwick,</hi> and many other of our Practical Divines that might be named; among which, I would by no means have omitted the excellent Works of Dr. <hi>Thomas Goodwin</hi> and Mr. <hi>Jo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeph Caryl;</hi> which Authors, and ſuch like, when they have read over, and well digeſted, they will undoubtedly, with the Bleſſing of God upon their ſtudies, become able men to preach the Goſpel, and defend the true <hi>Proteſtant Religion</hi> againſt all Gainſayers whatſoever; yea, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:52086:11"/>
in all probability, will attain unto ſuch an <hi>Eloquence</hi> and <hi>fluency</hi> of Speech, ſuch a <hi>ſweetneſs</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> of knowledge in <hi>Goſpel-truths,</hi> and ſuch a <hi>melting</hi> and <hi>moving</hi> way of preaching, as will render them <hi>bleſſed Inſtruments</hi> of much ſpiritual good to their Hearers. O what a <hi>joyful ſound</hi> all over the three Kingdoms would ſuch <hi>ſilver Trumpets</hi> as theſe make! and what <hi>golden Candleſticks</hi> with <hi>burning</hi> and <hi>ſhining Lights</hi> in them would be ſet up where-ere they come!</p>
            <p>This is the firſt moſt advantageous uſe (as I humbly conceive) and moſt of all tending to the Glory of God and the true publick Good, which ſuch rich <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> as aforeſaid, might make of the <hi>Wealth</hi> and <hi>Abundance</hi> which the Lord hath given them. If any Deſign in the world be worthy to be accounted a <hi>Noble Deſign,</hi> ſurely this is, thus to propagate the <hi>truly Reformed Proteſtant Religion;</hi> and eſpecially at <hi>ſuch a time</hi> as this is, to <hi>revive</hi> it, as it were, out of its own Aſhes.</p>
            <p>The founding of Hoſpitals for the relief of <hi>aged</hi> and <hi>needy</hi> people, is a good Act; and the ſetting the <hi>poor</hi> on work, is another; ſo is the binding out of poor Children to be Apprentices, and thereby be made able to live, and be uſeful in the world; but <hi>this,</hi> methinks, is a work <hi>beyond</hi> them all; and indeed, at this time, and in this Age, of greateſt <hi>neceſſity</hi> and <hi>importance.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The conſideration whereof, I ſuppoſe, was one of the chiefeſt Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that ſtirred up thoſe <hi>two moſt worthy Patriots,</hi> Eraſmus Smith and Thomas Foley <hi>
                  <abbr>Eſq</abbr>
               </hi> (both yet alive) to erect their Famous Schools of <hi>Grammar-Learning,</hi> and deviſe ſuch Statutes and Orders for the good Government and Education of the <hi>numerous Youth</hi> in them, as might moſt conduce unto this <hi>very end:</hi> three of which ſaid Schools were Founded by the ſaid <hi>Eraſmus Smith</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> ſome few years ſince in <hi>Ire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land,</hi> with a Revenue amounting, in ſome ſhort time, if well mana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged, to no leſs than <hi>fourteen hundred pound</hi> per annum (as I am aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>redly informed) given for ever, for the maintenance and ſupport of them. The other, very lately by the ſaid <hi>Thomas Foley</hi> 
               <abbr>Eſq</abbr> in <hi>Worce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterſhire,</hi> with an <hi>ample Revenue</hi> likewiſe for the upholding of it.</p>
            <p>Rare Examples, and highly worthy of imitation, were there any to be found <hi>ſo well minded!</hi> Perhaps ſome may be found; we will hope the beſt: and ſhould this little Treatiſe any way conduce thereunto, how ſhould I think it a <hi>Mercy</hi> and <hi>Honour,</hi> that ever God put it into my heart to write it, and thereby occaſion any to engage in ſo <hi>bleſſed a Work.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If it be objected, how can this be done, if men had never ſo good a mind to it? For are not places of Publick Education every where
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:52086:11"/>
grown <hi>ſo corrupt,</hi> and debauched, that ſuch as fear God dare not ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venture their Children in them; for how <hi>hopeful</hi> ſoever they may be when they come thither; yet have not <hi>too many</hi> found by ſad experience, the <hi>power</hi> of the <hi>Temptations</hi> they have there met with, even to their utter undoing?</p>
            <p>I anſwer, That were it once reſolved upon by the <hi>rich Proteſtants</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, as they live ſcattered up and down the <hi>Three Kingdoms,</hi> and care taken by them to educate <hi>ſuch Youths</hi> in every <hi>City, Great Town,</hi> and <hi>Countrey,</hi> and this known to be ſo; no doubt is to be made, but as <hi>good Schoolmaſters</hi> would be found, to do their parts without the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſities;</hi> ſo <hi>good Tutors</hi> would ſeat themſelves within the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> to receive <hi>Pupils</hi> from all parts, that ſhould be ſent to them: Perhaps indeed they might not be admitted into the Colledges upon the account of <hi>Nonconformity;</hi> but yet perhaps they might be admitted to <hi>inhabit</hi> ſomewhere without the Colledges, as <hi>Students</hi> from all parts of the world do in the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> abroad; as at <hi>Leyden, <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht, Padua, Paris, Heidelburg,</hi> and many others; by means whereof, they may be preſent at all <hi>publick Diſputations, Lectures,</hi> and other <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity-Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſes,</hi> and bear their ſhare in them, and in due time take their Degrees too (if not <hi>enſnared</hi> with <hi>Oaths,</hi> or otherwiſe hindered) and be as eminent in all parts of Learning, as any others; but if our <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> here at home, will not admit them to live among them, but <hi>exterminate</hi> and caſt them out, they might be ſent by their <hi>Benefactors</hi> to the <hi>beſt <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſities</hi> abroad, particularly to <hi>Cambridg</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> who are wont to admit of <hi>Strangers,</hi> and that gladly too, from whatſoever parts they come. <hi>O happy day would that be, could we once ſee it!</hi> if the ſeveral hundreds of ſuch <hi>rich Proteſtants,</hi> as aforeſaid, which might be found in theſe <hi>Kingdoms,</hi> would ſet apart ſome <hi>Annual Revenue</hi> to continue for ever, for ſo <hi>brave a Service;</hi> how many thouſands of pounds yearly might be raiſed with eaſe, and diſpoſed of <hi>this way?</hi> and how many hundreds of <hi>hopeful young Branches</hi> might thus continually from time to time, ſpring up to <hi>ſucceed</hi> the <hi>old ones</hi> that decay ſo faſt, and die daily?</p>
            <p>Methought it very much affected me many years ſince, when I ſaw at the <hi>Jeſuites-School</hi> at <hi>Antwerp,</hi> a great number of the <hi>Flower</hi> of the Youth of the <hi>City</hi> and <hi>Countrey</hi> thereabout, to be trained up in a Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion <hi>ſo wicked</hi> and <hi>Idolatrous</hi> as the <hi>Popiſh</hi> Religion is; ſhall theſe men of ſo <hi>falſe a Religion</hi> be ſo ſedulous and careful to raiſe up a ſucceſſion of able inſtruments to maintain their <hi>rotten Cauſe,</hi> and not think the moſt <hi>ripe-witted</hi> and very <hi>beſt-Parted</hi> of their Children to be at all <hi>diſpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged,</hi> but much <hi>honoured</hi> rather, to be ſo employed? And ſhall <hi>Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants</hi>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:52086:12"/>
be otherwiſe minded concerning their Children, and <hi>leſs careful</hi> for their Religion?</p>
            <p>And though I judge this <hi>firſt means</hi> now named, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>education</hi> of <hi>Youths</hi> in <hi>ſound Religion</hi> and <hi>good Learning,</hi> to be the ſpeedieſt and very beſt that can be propounded for <hi>retriving</hi> and <hi>advancing</hi> of true <hi>Proteſtantiſm,</hi> yet I conceive <hi>other methods</hi> added thereunto, will yet give ſome <hi>farther</hi> good help therein: and therefore,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> I do farther humbly move that the aforeſaid <hi>rich Proteſtants</hi> will make another <hi>Annual Proviſion</hi> to continue for ever, for the teaching of poor Children, both Males and Females, to <hi>read the Scriptures,</hi> and to learn ſome <hi>good Catechiſmes,</hi> containing <hi>full</hi> and <hi>clear</hi> Inſtructions in all the <hi>principal</hi> and <hi>neceſſary Points</hi> of the true <hi>Reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and this in every place throughout theſe <hi>Kingdoms;</hi> eſpecially in thoſe <hi>Cities, Great Towns</hi> and <hi>Villages,</hi> where the poor do <hi>most abound,</hi> and where is <hi>greatest Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs;</hi> and that <hi>yearly Salaries</hi> may be ſetled to be conſtantly and duly paid to <hi>Schoolmaſters</hi> and <hi>School<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſtreſſes</hi> to that end; and alſo that ſome <hi>Reward</hi> be given to <hi>ſuch</hi> of the ſaid Children (ſuppoſe a Bible, or ſuch like) that are <hi>quickest</hi> in their Learning, and ſhall have firſt read over the <hi>Bible,</hi> and can give the <hi>best account</hi> of their <hi>Catechiſm;</hi> this would much encreaſe a good <hi>emulation</hi> among them, and by an <hi>holy craft</hi> engraft the knowledge of Chriſt in them.</p>
            <p>Rewards likewiſe of this kind, or a certain ſum of money allotted yearly to ſuch <hi>aged people</hi> and <hi>poor ſervants,</hi> whether Males or Females, as cannot read but by their <hi>own induſtry,</hi> with ſuch helps as they can get, do at laſt attain unto it, and can <hi>make proof</hi> thereof; and farther, that having learned thus to read, they do <hi>dayly ſpend ſome time</hi> in reading the Bible and ſome good Catechiſmes, would be money <hi>well gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven.</hi> Who knows what even <hi>ſuch a meaſure</hi> of knowledge as many an one may get <hi>this way,</hi> may do? Who knows how many a <hi>precious ſoul</hi> may be ſaved by it? I am ſure no better courſe can be taken to <hi>ſpread abroad</hi> the light of truth, the rules of holineſs, and to <hi>chaſe away Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance</hi> and <hi>Prophaneneſs,</hi> where it abounds moſt, nor where people are <hi>thus inſtructed,</hi> would the <hi>buſie Papiſts</hi> and their <hi>Emiſſaries</hi> be able to ſeduce <hi>ſo many,</hi> as 'tis juſtly to be feared they now do, and will do, eſpecially in the <hi>dark</hi> and <hi>remote parts</hi> of theſe <hi>Kingdoms.</hi> And as in all places, thus to provide and raiſe up <hi>choice Inſtruments,</hi> and to inſtruct poor <hi>ignorant</hi> Creatures, whether <hi>old</hi> or <hi>young,</hi> in manner aforeſaid, and for the ends aforeſaid, would be an <hi>excellent work;</hi> ſo to do it there moſt of all, where is moſt need, will be moſt <hi>praiſe-worthy;</hi> as in <hi>Wales</hi>
               <pb n="19" facs="tcp:52086:12"/>
(eſpecially in <hi>North-wales,</hi> and ſuch of the <hi>Northern-Countries,</hi> and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther parts of <hi>England,</hi> as are moſt <hi>ignorant</hi> of God, and are <hi>leaſt able,</hi> without the helps aforeſaid, to train up their Children, either for <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Service,</hi> or at leaſt, ſo far as to be able in their <hi>own Mother-Tongue,</hi> whether <hi>Welch</hi> or <hi>Engliſh,</hi> to read and know the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And becauſe of all parts of His <hi>Majeſties Dominions,</hi> the poor <hi>Welch Countries</hi> ſeem to be <hi>moſt destitute</hi> of the ſaving Knowledge of God, and the <hi>means</hi> of it, partly for want of <hi>Bibles, Catechiſms</hi> and other good Books in the <hi>Welch Tongue;</hi> and partly for want of learned and good men, <hi>able</hi> to preach in <hi>that Language</hi> to them, I therefore hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly propound on behalf of the ſaid <hi>Welch</hi> people, to all <hi>conſiderate</hi> per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, whether it would not be <hi>another moſt excellent work</hi> of <hi>Piety, Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Charity</hi> and <hi>Pity</hi> to Souls, if the <hi>rich Proteſtants,</hi> living in thoſe Countries, or elſewhere, ſhould ſet apart an <hi>Annual Revenue</hi> for ever, for the maintaining of ſuch good and able men to preach in the <hi>Welch Tongue:</hi> to ſuch of them as underſtand no other; I mean, ſuch peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly-minded <hi>Nonconforming Miniſters,</hi> as by reaſon of their <hi>Nonconformi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty,</hi> how peaceably-minded ſoever they be, cannot be capable of the publick maintenance. And as a <hi>farther help</hi> to the ſaving knowledge of Chriſt in thoſe parts, I once more humbly propound, whether it would not be a <hi>worthy work</hi> for the aforeſaid <hi>rich Proteſtants,</hi> to take care that every year, an <hi>Impreſſion</hi> of <hi>Welch Bibles,</hi> and the worthy Labours of ſome of the chiefeſt of our <hi>ſoundeſt Practical Divines</hi> be likewiſe turned into the <hi>Welch Tongue,</hi> and <hi>printed,</hi> and given to ſuch as ſhall be found <hi>moſt deſirous</hi> of them, but <hi>not able</hi> to purchaſe them; and this courſe to continue from year to year, till there be a <hi>ſufficient ſtore</hi> of Bibles, and other good Books in <hi>that Language,</hi> for the uſe of the ſaid <hi>Welch</hi> Countries.</p>
            <p>But methinks I hear ſome ſay, All the ways and means here pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for the reſtoring of the <hi>true Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and the far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther advancement of it, are <hi>very good;</hi> and no doubt is to be made, but bleſſed effects will come of it, were they ſpeedily and vigorouſly proſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuted and put in practice; but who can perſwade <hi>diſſenting Brethren</hi> to ſuch an amicable, ſincere and hearty cloſure, as is deſired? Who can <hi>perſwade</hi> the <hi>Parents</hi> of Children every where, and others, that are the Governors of Families, or any way have the <hi>care of Souls,</hi> to lay ſound knowledge into the minds of ſuch as are committed to their charge, by <hi>Catechetical Inſtructions</hi> as hath been ſuggeſted? Who can perſwade old and young to <hi>take pains</hi> in going from houſe to houſe, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonally to converſe each with other, for mutual and further edifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion?
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:52086:13"/>
Laſtly, Who can perſwade the <hi>rich Proteſtants</hi> every where, to lay out the <hi>whole,</hi> or any <hi>part</hi> of their Eſtates in the ſeveral wayes, and for the <hi>pious</hi> ends propounded? Alas! theſe are great things, and not to be hoped for in this Age, a much better Spirit muſt be found a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong all ſorts of men, before ſuch <hi>Counſels</hi> as theſe will take place.</p>
            <p>I confeſs, 'tis true, the work is <hi>difficult,</hi> and not to be in the leaſt attempted (much leſs is it like to be accompliſhed) by any <hi>humane power;</hi> but as difficult as it is, and ſeemingly, even impoſſible; yet me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinks one way remains that may render it not only <hi>feaſable,</hi> but eaſily <hi>practicable</hi> alſo, and expeditiouſly proſperous, and that is, the <hi>power of God</hi> put forth upon the hearts of men; he is the <hi>Lord God Omnipotent,</hi> reigning and ruling in, and over all his Creatures; <hi>he doth whatſoever he pleaſeth both in Heaven and in Earth;</hi> if he ſay the word, and give out his command, even to the moſt obſtinate, and <hi>invincibly inflexible</hi> to any thing that is good, they preſently obey; he that can <hi>cleave the Rocks</hi> aſunder, <hi>melt</hi> the Mountains, and turn the <hi>whole <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſe</hi> upſide down, what cannot he do upon the Spirit, the Mind and Soul of any one whatſoever, to <hi>turn</hi> and <hi>encline</hi> it which way he pleaſeth?</p>
            <p>Well then, this I ſuppoſe will be granted, that how <hi>fierce</hi> and <hi>keen</hi> ſoever <hi>diſſenting Brethren</hi> have been, and ſtill are, one towards another, how <hi>moroſe, ſharp, froward</hi> ſoever; yet he can take off that <hi>ferocity,</hi> that <hi>ferity</hi> and <hi>fierceneſs,</hi> and put them into a <hi>meek</hi> and <hi>humble</hi> temper; he that can make <hi>Lions to lie down with Lambs, and Leopards with Kids,</hi> ſure can make the <hi>Lambs</hi> and the <hi>Kids</hi> to agree among themſelves; he that can give that <hi>wiſdom</hi> (where 'tis wanting) <hi>which is from above, and is firſt pure, then peaceable, gentle, and eaſie to be entreated;</hi> he can <hi>quickly, faſtly, firmly, ſweetly</hi> unite all his people, and ſo in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner he can <hi>perſwade</hi> to all the reſt of the Matters now propounded.</p>
            <p>If it be ſaid, All this we know God can do; for who can hinder <hi>Omnipotence</hi> it ſelf from doing whatever it hath a mind to? But what <hi>ground</hi> have we, or can we have to believe that he <hi>will</hi> do it?</p>
            <p>I Anſwer, could we ſee but <hi>one thing</hi> generally practiſed by all <hi>true-hearted ſound Proteſtants,</hi> throughout theſe three <hi>Kingdomes,</hi> viz. a <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtant courſe of earneſt and fervent Prayer</hi> kept on foot. Could we ſee the <hi>Spirit of Grace and Supplication poured forth upon the Houſe of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>and the Inhabitants of our Goſpel</hi>-Jeruſalem, for the obtaining of the Particulars afore-mentioned, by ſetting the <hi>power of God</hi> on work to effect them; I think there would be <hi>good ground</hi> to affirm, even without all peradventure, that he <hi>will</hi> do it, at leaſt <hi>ſo far,</hi> as ſhall make for
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:52086:13"/>
his <hi>own Glory,</hi> and the accompliſhment of whatſoever <hi>good</hi> he intends for his people. And among other Arguments, I ſhall mention only theſe three, to perſwade to a <hi>Belief</hi> thereof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That he is, and alwayes will be <hi>willing to hear</hi> his Peoples prayers, and that in any thing they ſhall call upon him for (provided they pray aright, from right <hi>Principles,</hi> in a right <hi>manner,</hi> and to right <hi>ends</hi>) is evident from his <hi>Nature;</hi> he is a God of a moſt <hi>merciful, ſweet</hi> and <hi>gracious</hi> diſpoſition; the Scripture every where deſcribes him ſo; a God <hi>full of Bowels;</hi> he hath his <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, his <hi>tenerrimos motus,</hi> his tender mercies, <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>Bowels of Mercy</hi> and Commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions. This Chriſt himſelf bears witneſs to, <hi>Luke</hi> 18.7, 8. Where, af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter he had put forth a <hi>Parable</hi> from the <hi>unjuſt Judge</hi> to the poor oppreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Widow, and did it <hi>to the end, that men ought alwayes to pray, and not to faint;</hi> he adds theſe words, if the importunity of the poor wi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow with the unjuſt Judge, prevailed for juſtice, though he otherwiſe had <hi>no mind</hi> to do her Juſtice, <hi>ſhall not God</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>avenge his own Elect, which cry night and day unto him, though he bear long with them? I tell you that he will avenge them ſpeedily.</hi> He is ſo <hi>propenſe</hi> to Mercy, I, and to Juſtice too, that whenever his people cry unto him, he will ſhew them mercy in the very <hi>execution</hi> of his Juſtice upon his Enemies: But mark here, when will he do this? when they <hi>cry</hi> unto him, when they <hi>ſigh</hi> and <hi>groan</hi> out their Complaints, as the poor <hi>Iſraelites</hi> did under their <hi>Oppreſſions</hi> in <hi>Egypt,</hi> and as <hi>Daniel</hi> and the <hi>three Children</hi> did in the <hi>fiery Furnace</hi> and the <hi>Lion's Den; The ſighings of his Priſoners came up before him,</hi> Pſal. 79.11.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It is likewiſe evident that it is, and muſt needs be ſo; namely, that God is, and <hi>alwayes will be willing to hear his Peoples pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> (when for matter and manner they pray aright, as was before hinted) from the <hi>Engagement</hi> which he is under, and hath freely laid upon himſelf, ſo to do; for hath he not promiſed, and that often, that <hi>when<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever his people pray unto him, and ſeek him with their whole heart, they ſhall be ſure to find him?</hi> Nay, hath he not commanded, that they ſhould <hi>call upon him in time of trouble?</hi> and then backed that command with a <hi>ſpecial aſſurance</hi> given, that when they do ſo cry, <hi>he will give a gracious Audience?</hi> Pſal. 50.15. compared with <hi>Jer.</hi> 29.12, 13, 14. Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudes of Paſſages in <hi>Holy Writ</hi> put this altogether out of queſtion; a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong which I cannot omit to mention that moſt <hi>emphatical place</hi> in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 65.24. <hi>It ſhall come to paſs that before they call</hi> (the Prophet ſpeaks it of the Lord's people) <hi>I will anſwer</hi> before they call! Mark that; God will be <hi>more ready to anſwer than they to call, mere ready to hear than they
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:52086:14"/>
to ſpeak;</hi> and this alſo, doth not our bleſſed Saviour more than once bear witneſs to concerning his <hi>Father;</hi> namely, That <hi>whatſoever we ask of the Father in his Name, he will give it,</hi> John 15.16. &amp; chap. 16.23.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> For farther confirmation unto this great and bleſſed Truth, that <hi>God is willing to hear his Peoples Prayers,</hi> hath he not left ſtore of <hi>Inſtances</hi> upon record, that <hi>de facto</hi> he hath done ſo, and that from <hi>age to age,</hi> throughout all generations? Did he not hear the <hi>Groanings</hi> of the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> under their <hi>cruel Taskmaſters</hi> in <hi>Egypt?</hi> Did he not hear the <hi>Cries</hi> of the <hi>poor captive Jews</hi> in <hi>Babylon,</hi> and at laſt bring them out from thence? Did not the Supplications of <hi>Ezra, Nehemiah, Daniel,</hi> in the three ninth Chapters of their ſeveral Books, come up to Heaven, and <hi>find acceptance,</hi> both for themſelves, and all the reſt of their <hi>diſtreſſed Brethren?</hi> Did not the Prayers of <hi>Mordecai</hi> and the <hi>per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexed Jews</hi> in <hi>Shuſhan,</hi> added to thoſe of Queen <hi>Eſther</hi> and her Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dens, prevail againſt proud <hi>Haman?</hi> Did not the Cries of <hi>Jonah,</hi> even <hi>out of the Belly</hi> of the Whale, find a paſſage through the <hi>ſurging waves?</hi> and prove ſo quick, even with their <hi>watry wings,</hi> that they <hi>came in un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to God, even unto his holy Temple?</hi> as the expreſſion is, <hi>Jonah</hi> 2.7. Time would fail to relate the <hi>pleaſant ſtories</hi> to this purpoſe, which ſtand up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on record, not only in the Scriptures of the Old and New Teſtament, but alſo in <hi>all other</hi> Eccleſiaſtick Story.</p>
            <p>Well then, the <hi>Premiſes conſidered</hi> what remains, but that I now call upon all <hi>true-hearted Proteſtants</hi> throughout theſe three Kingdoms, that they would take encouragement from <hi>hence,</hi> and ſet upon this <hi>pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-work</hi> with all poſſible ſpeed and vigour; eſpecially two things more being farther conſidered.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> That God is as <hi>willing</hi> to hear Prayers <hi>now as ever, as kind, as merciful, and as much engaged to his People</hi> that truly fear him, and ſeek unto him, <hi>as ever,</hi> and will be as faithful in <hi>performing</hi> with his Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple as ever he was.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> That the ſtate of the true Reformed Proteſtant Church and People of God <hi>never had more need</hi> of Prayer; never was at a <hi>lower ebb</hi> than now, never had more <hi>numerous and potent enemies</hi> to grapple with, ſince the times of Reformation came in among us.</p>
            <p>Theſe arguments one would think ſhould have force enough in them, with all <hi>good</hi> and <hi>ſound-hearted Chriſtians,</hi> to put them upon this ſo <hi>needful, ſeaſonable,</hi> and (if well managed) <hi>ſucceſsful Duty of Prayer;</hi> a Duty, which hath done ſuch <hi>wonders</hi> in all ages; the <hi>prevalency</hi> of which hath been atteſted by ſo <hi>rich experience</hi> in them that have made <hi>trial</hi> of it; a Duty which God himſelf <hi>calls</hi> us ſo much unto,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:52086:14"/>
takes ſo much <hi>delight</hi> in, and hath encouraged by ſo <hi>many</hi> Promiſes. 'Tis true, the Devil is a great enemy to it, and evil-minded men op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe it what they can, becauſe where this is much in uſe, it <hi>greatly fights</hi> againſt and keeps down the <hi>Dominion</hi> of Sin and Satan, not only in the hearts of <hi>particular</hi> men and women, but in whole <hi>States</hi> and <hi>Kingdoms.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>If any ſay, it is indeed a Command, and ſo a <hi>neceſsary</hi> as well as a very <hi>profitable</hi> Duty, and God forbid but it ſhould every where be much in practice, in every <hi>Cloſet,</hi> in every <hi>Family,</hi> in every <hi>publick</hi> and <hi>ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemn</hi> Congregation, at the due times and ſeaſons of it; but what do you mean when you call ſo earneſtly upon the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> to pray? do you mean to perſwade them to break the <hi>King's Laws</hi> by <hi>Conventicling</hi> and meeting together in great numbers for this Duty? 'tis ſome <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinary</hi> kind of praying ſure, you intend by this your ſo <hi>zealous</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation to it. To which I anſwer.</p>
            <p>It is indeed an <hi>extraordinary Spirit of Prayer</hi> which I long to ſee in all the Lord's people, there being ſuch <hi>extraordinary occaſions</hi> for it; and therefore beſides the <hi>ſecret, private</hi> and <hi>publick</hi> Prayers before men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, in <hi>Cloſets, Families,</hi> and <hi>ſolemn Congregations</hi> in times of publick Worſhip; it is the <hi>vehement deſire</hi> of my Soul, that they would once <hi>every week</hi> at leaſt, <hi>ſet apart</hi> ſome time, more or leſs, as may conſiſt with their ſeveral Callings and Employments, to <hi>call upon God by earneſt Prayer,</hi> and this all over the Three Kingdoms, where-ever any true praying Saints can be found, that can conveniently meet toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: which to do, and that with <hi>mighty wreſtlings,</hi> as <hi>Jacob</hi> did, when in danger of his Brother <hi>Eſau,</hi> I underſtand not how it is a breach of any of the King's Laws, unleſs the late Law againſt <hi>Religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Meetings</hi> be intended; but to grant ſuch Meetings as theſe to be abſolutely unlawful in themſelves, or to be intended by that Law, I underſtand not any further, than that the number <hi>beyond four</hi> (beſides the Houſe-keeper) in ſuch Meetings, may by that Law render them <hi>criminal:</hi> but where <hi>offence</hi> is taken at the number exceeding what the Law directs, why may not the good people of <hi>England</hi> make up their Meetings <hi>in that very number which is allowed,</hi> rather than not to meet at all; or ſo meet as to give <hi>offence</hi> unto the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate?</hi> Will not the number of forty perſons, meeting in eight or ten <hi>diſtinct compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nies,</hi> be as <hi>prevalent</hi> with God, as if they all made up but <hi>one Meeting?</hi> and will not the <hi>Gifts</hi> and <hi>Graces</hi> of many more particular perſons be thus <hi>exerciſed,</hi> than can be, if all theſe eight or ten Meetings were uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted together in one?</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="24" facs="tcp:52086:15"/>But now the next thing to be conſidered, is, what ſhould be the <hi>principal ſubject Matter</hi> of this <hi>ſpecial</hi> and <hi>extraordinary</hi> Meeting toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in Prayer? This indeed to be unanimouſly agreed upon, and eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry where, as it were, <hi>uno tenore,</hi> with <hi>one conſent,</hi> to be put up by all <hi>praying Saints,</hi> would be very <hi>material,</hi> and much conducing to the ends for which it is here humbly moved; an <hi>univerſal Harmony</hi> and <hi>Agreement</hi> in the things prayed for, muſt needs be <hi>excellent,</hi> and, from the very <hi>agreement</hi> that is in it, be the <hi>more prevalent;</hi> for doth not Chriſt himſelf intimate ſo much unto his Diſciples, <hi>Matth.</hi> 18.19? <hi>If two of you ſhall agree (<gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>) on earth, as touching any thing that they ſhall ask, it ſhall be done for them of my Father which is in Heaven.</hi> If a right ſpiritual Prayer, wherein the <hi>Heart</hi> and the <hi>Mouth</hi> of any one that prayes alone, do <hi>agree together,</hi> be a <hi>Divine Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lody,</hi> ſweet and delicious <hi>Muſick</hi> in the ears of God, as himſelf tells us it is, <hi>Cant.</hi> 2.14. <hi>Let me hear thy voice</hi> (ſaith he) that is, her voice in prayer) <hi>for ſweet is thy voice;</hi> I ſay, if it be true thus of <hi>one ſingle</hi> perſon praying alone, muſt it not needs be ſo <hi>much more</hi> when the hearts, minds and ſpirits of <hi>divers agree together,</hi> when met about that bleſſed work? Inſtances for this might be given; take one inſtead of many: It is that of the Prophet <hi>Malachi,</hi> chap. 3.16. where we thus read, <hi>Then they that feared the Lord ſpake often one to another</hi> (and alſo one with another in this Duty of Prayer) <hi>and the Lord hearkned and heard,</hi> obſerve the Paſſage; he <hi>hearkned,</hi> as men do to ſome <hi>rare conſort of Mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſick;</hi> and ſo indeed the word <hi>Symphony</hi> uſed by our Saviour himſelf, in the place before-quoted, every one knows, that knows any thing of the <hi>Greek Tongue,</hi> doth properly ſignifie an Harmony of Voices, or of Inſtruments, or both together: Thus <hi>Novarinus</hi> in locum; <hi>Verbo Graeco elegans ſubeſt Metaphora,</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, <hi>de Muſico vocum concentu har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monico<expan>
                     <am>
                        <g ref="char:abque"/>
                     </am>
                     <ex>que</ex>
                  </expan> ſono dicitur, tanquam ſi diceretur, non minus gratam eſſ Deo comordem plurium orationem quam Concentus Muſicus hominum auribus ſit gratus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This then being a good reaſon for <hi>ſuch an agreement</hi> in the matter of ſuch <hi>extraordinary</hi> Prayer, as I humby move may be <hi>every where</hi> ſet on foot, and conſtantly kept up, in the practice of it, till the <hi>Scene</hi> of things be ſo <hi>altered,</hi> that the <hi>Harmony</hi> of Prayer, may be put into a <hi>new Tune</hi> of Praiſes. Among other Petitions which it ſhall pleaſe the Lord by his <hi>good Spirit</hi> to frame in the hearts of all praying Saints, I con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive the <hi>Matters mentioned</hi> in the foregoing Diſcourſe, will be very <hi>pertinent</hi> and ſeaſonable, as <hi>purſuant</hi> to the ends deſigned by it; namely,</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:52086:15"/>That all the Particulars before diſcourſed upon in this ſmall Treatiſe, <hi>viz.</hi> a <hi>ſweet Harmony</hi> and <hi>Agreement</hi> between all <hi>diſſenting Parties,</hi> a conſcientious performance of all the before-mentioned <hi>Family-Duties,</hi> may be every where ſet on foot; with ſuch other Methods as are pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pounded for the encreaſe of knowledge, and the eſtabliſhing of the minds of people in the <hi>truly Reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> now ſo much <hi>ſtruck</hi> at; and eſpecially, that God would pleaſe to ſtir up the <hi>Rich Proteſtants</hi> to the forementioned works of Piety and Charity, for the preſervation of the ſaid <hi>truly Reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livering of it down to the Generations that are to come.</p>
            <p>If <hi>earneſt</hi> Prayer be put up for this, and that <hi>univerſally,</hi> by all that know how to pray, throughout all theſe <hi>Three Kingdoms,</hi> namely, on behalf of theſe <hi>Rich Proteſtants,</hi> as well as in the other particulars beforementioned, who can tell, what a <hi>choice publick Spirit</hi> God may put into them? He can make even the <hi>Niggard bountiful, and the Churl liberal;</hi> he can open the <hi>Hearts, Hands, Purſes,</hi> and poſſeſs the <hi>minds</hi> of thouſands with the <hi>excellent Service</hi> they may do this way; not only to the <hi>preſent,</hi> but the <hi>Future Ages:</hi> He can tell them, and ſet it home upon them, that they cannot poſſibly <hi>honour the Lord with their ſubſtance more effectually</hi> in this world, than to ſet it a running in the forementioned <hi>Channels,</hi> that by this means, that is, by propaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting and delivering down the <hi>true Proteſtant Religion</hi> to all poſterity, by ſuch an uſe of their Eſtates, as aforeſaid, will <hi>greatly turn unto their ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> both here and hereafter.</p>
            <p>Firſt here; even in <hi>this</hi> life, and that <hi>many</hi> wayes; for will they not hereby, not only provide for many <hi>poor Childrens</hi> outward ſubſiſtence and livelihood in this world? But which is a <hi>greater thing,</hi> give ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage to the <hi>improvement</hi> of the Parts and Natural Gifts of many a <hi>Fine Wit</hi> for publick Services, that otherwiſe would be in a manner <hi>wholly lost,</hi> and become <hi>uſeleſs,</hi> both in Church and State, for want of an <hi>ingenious</hi> education? And, which is yet more, will they not keep up a <hi>learned</hi> and <hi>able Miniſtry;</hi> and thereby, in time, make up the <hi>la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mented loſs</hi> of thoſe many famous, <hi>burning and ſhining Lights,</hi> which of late years have been <hi>extinguiſhed,</hi> and ſtill are more and more extin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guiſhed every day? and will they not by this means likewiſe, have the <hi>Prayers</hi> of <hi>Multitudes continually ſent</hi> up to Heaven for them, that <hi>Bleſſings</hi> of all ſorts may be poured down upon <hi>them</hi> and <hi>theirs?</hi> Yea, and will not (as the Apoſtle ſayes in much the like caſe, 2. <hi>Cor.</hi> 9.11, 12, 13.) this very thing, namely, this bountifulneſs and liberal diſtri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bution for ſo <hi>brave a Service</hi> unto the Saints (as well thoſe that are not
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:52086:16"/>
yet born, as thoſe that are) cauſe <hi>many Thanksgivings unto God?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Hereafter, at the great Tribunal of God; how <hi>great a reward</hi> will it lay up for them, and how <hi>high a place</hi> will it mount them to in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven? all thoſe <hi>thouſands</hi> of men and women that ſhall come to a true knowledge of God, and the ſaving of their <hi>precious Souls;</hi> in after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ages, as a <hi>conſequence and effect of this their ſo pious diſpoſal of their wealth,</hi> will they not paſs for ſuch as they have ſome way been <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrumental</hi> in the ſaving of? The <hi>Converſions</hi> wrought by thoſe men, which they ſhall have brought up, and have given a <hi>liberal and holy E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ducation</hi> to, will they not, in part, be <hi>aſcribed to them?</hi> The Rule in Philoſophy is true here, <hi>Cauſa cauſae est cauſa cauſati;</hi> in all <hi>noble acts,</hi> the <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>remote Cauſe</hi> is to be acknowledged the <hi>ſpring</hi> and <hi>fountain</hi> of the next and more immediate cauſes and the good effects thereof.</p>
            <p>When <hi>ſtout</hi> and <hi>valiant Champions</hi> which they inſtrumentally ſhall have thus raiſed up, not only for the <hi>propagating</hi> of the truly <hi>Reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> but for a <hi>ſtrenuous defence</hi> of it alſo, againſt <hi>all Op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſers</hi> whatſoever; and when the minds of people, every where, ſhall thereby be ſo <hi>fixed and eſtabliſhed,</hi> as to be able to ſtand againſt all <hi>ſhocks</hi> and <hi>ſtorms,</hi> ſo that no <hi>Errors,</hi> no <hi>Powers,</hi> no <hi>Factions, Conſpira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies, Subtilties,</hi> or <hi>combined intereſt</hi> of a <hi>Popiſh Party;</hi> no <hi>Prieſts</hi> or <hi>Jeſuites,</hi> or their <hi>Adherents</hi> ſhall be ever able to <hi>hinder</hi> the growth of true <hi>Proteſtantiſm;</hi> much leſs <hi>exterminate</hi> it out of theſe Kingdomes: what matter of <hi>Joy</hi> will this be to all ſuch <hi>Rich Proteſtants,</hi> as upon the <hi>conſecrating</hi> of their Eſtates to the uſes aforeſaid, ſhall ſee ſuch <hi>bleſſed effects and fruits</hi> thereof; yea, and as was before ſaid, what <hi>high re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward</hi> too ſhall they be ſure to be <hi>enriched</hi> with in the other world upon this account?</p>
            <p>But now on the contrary, how much otherwiſe will it be with all ſuch <hi>rich Proteſtants,</hi> eſpecially ſuch of them as <hi>pretend to a profeſſion of Religion</hi> (and it may be, amongſt the moſt zealous Proteſtants too) and yet have hearts ſo <hi>eaten into,</hi> yea ſo <hi>eaten up,</hi> and even <hi>gangren'd</hi> with <hi>Covetouſneſs;</hi> that,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>First,</hi> They are ſo far from doing good to others with the <hi>abundance of wealth</hi> which they reckon themſelves <hi>Maſters of,</hi> that they live like <hi>ſlaves</hi> themſelves to it, ſo <hi>penuriouſly,</hi> ſo <hi>ſparingly,</hi> ſo <hi>pinchingly,</hi> that every <hi>wiſe obſerver</hi> of them cannot but <hi>wonder</hi> at their folly, and every good man <hi>pity it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> When any opportunity is offered them for <hi>advancing</hi> any work of <hi>publick</hi> or <hi>private Charity,</hi> be the <hi>neceſſity</hi> and <hi>excellency</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of never ſo <hi>viſible</hi> and <hi>apparent;</hi> yet, they either find <hi>pitiful excuſes,</hi> or
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:52086:16"/>
               <hi>frivolous Arguments</hi> againſt it, and ſo plainly <hi>reject</hi> it; or, if <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> part with any thing, it is in ſo <hi>ſmall a pittance,</hi> and with ſo much <hi>pain</hi> and <hi>difficulty,</hi> as if they were letting out ſo much of their <hi>Heart-blood.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I ſay concerning ſuch <hi>miſerably-minded rich men</hi> as theſe, how <hi>lamen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table</hi> is their condition here? and how <hi>much more lamentable</hi> is it like to be hereafter? for the <hi>evincing</hi> of both which, it would be well for this <hi>ſort</hi> of men <hi>frequently</hi> and with all <hi>ſeriouſneſs,</hi> to read and conſider theſe following <hi>great Scripture-Truths</hi> wherein they are deeply concerned, and for whoſe ſake, after an <hi>eſpecial manner,</hi> they ſeem to be made a part of the <hi>Divine Oracle,</hi> and to be left upon record.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The manifold <hi>miſchiefs, hurts</hi> and <hi>dangers</hi> that this <hi>wretched ſpirit</hi> of theirs inevitably <hi>hurries</hi> them into, as is expreſſed at large in <hi>Prov.</hi> 28.20, 22. and in <hi>Eccleſ.</hi> 5. from v. 10, to 18. compared with <hi>Mat.</hi> 13.22. 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 6.9, 10. <hi>Jam.</hi> 4.4, 5. from <hi>v.</hi> 1, to 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> With as much <hi>ſeriouſneſs</hi> and <hi>frequency</hi> to <hi>read</hi> and <hi>conſider</hi> that paſſage, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3.17. <hi>Whoſo hath this world's good, and ſeeth his Brother have need, and ſhutteth up his Bowels of compaſſion from him, how dwelleth the love of God in him?</hi> And what advantage will he have by his <hi>wealth,</hi> if God hath no <hi>love</hi> for him, nor he for <hi>God</hi> and <hi>his people,</hi> in a right uſe and improvement of it?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Thirdly,</hi> and laſtly, Let them ſeriouſly conſider, that being but <hi>Stewards</hi> for God, and <hi>muſt give an account of their Stewardſhip;</hi> as is fully ſet forth in the <hi>Parable</hi> of the <hi>rich man's Steward,</hi> in <hi>Luke</hi> 16. <hi>Their account</hi> of all others, is like to be the <hi>moſt dreadful,</hi> and thereupon have they not need to uſe this, or the like Letany?</p>
            <p>
               <hi>From an exceſſive love unto, inſatiable deſires after the world, with a vehement and moſt eager purſuit thereof; from the ſordid ſpirit of the vile perſon, mentioned by the Prophet</hi> Iſaiah, <hi>chap.</hi> 32. from v. 5. to 8. <hi>from the God-provoking, ſoul-damning and deteſtable ſin of Covetouſneſs, which is Idolatry; from an excluſion out of Heaven, and the loſs of eternal life; from the Treaſures of wrath heaped up againſt the day of wrath, and from the everlaſting burnings of unquenchable flames among the Devils in Hell, which are the Miſer's portion;</hi> Good Lord deliver us.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="advert_for_book">
            <p>And now for a Cloſe of all, I will end with this <hi>earneſt requeſt</hi> and deſire, that all ſuch, eſpecially ſuch <hi>rich perſons</hi> as would be further in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructed and invited to the practice of what in this ſmall Treatiſe is here humbly offered, would purchaſe to themſelves, and carefully read over a Book of <hi>ſmall price;</hi> but as <hi>pithy</hi> a Book, and as <hi>argumentative</hi> though in a plain ſtile) as any I know. The Title of it is, <hi>The Sureſt and
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:52086:17"/>
Safeſt Way of Thriving;</hi> Publiſhed by Mr. <hi>Tho. Gouge,</hi> Miniſter of the Goſpel: And Printed for <hi>W. Rawlins</hi> at the <hi>Hand and Pen</hi> over againſt the <hi>Royal Exchange</hi> in <hi>Cornhil,</hi> 1673.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="text">
            <head>An Appendix.</head>
            <p>THe conſideration of two things, methinks, ſhould very <hi>much affect</hi> all ſound and true-hearted Proteſtants.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The <hi>great</hi> and <hi>continual decay</hi> of the <hi>old Stock</hi> of our Learned, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, Orthodox, Faithful, Laborious, <hi>Proteſtant Divines.</hi> How <hi>fast</hi> do they drop away? how do they die daily? And how are the Flocks and People they were Shepherds unto, every where left deſtitute? To ſay nothing of thoſe <hi>Famous Lights</hi> which were extinguiſhed in the <hi>foregoing Age, viz.</hi> the reverend Mr. <hi>Greenhams, Hilderſhams, Reynolds, Dods, Clevers, Scud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders, Twiſſes, Byfields, Batemans, Rogerſes, Capels, Boltons, Balls, Whartons, Wards, Bowleſes, Perkinſes, Ameſiuſſes, Straughtons, Har<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſſes, Pinks, Wheatleys, Whites, Wilſons,</hi> and hundreds more. What <hi>ſore blows</hi> in this kind have we received within this laſt <hi>twenty</hi> or <hi>five and twenty</hi> years? How many <hi>Marſhals, Burroughſes, Wilſons, Goodwins, Carters, Sympſons, Bonds, Jeanſes, Sydenhams, Palmers, Symonſes, Whitakers, Arrowſmiths, Youngs, Vineſes, Gatakers, Aſhes, Penns, Hills, Collinſes, Beadles, Fullers, Cawdreys,</hi> &amp;c? Yea, within this laſt <hi>fifteen</hi> years, how many <hi>Noltons, Taylors, Strongs, Slaters, Sedgewicks, Ruttons, Spurſtows, Burgeſſes, Helmſes, Hammonds?</hi> Yea, within one <hi>five</hi> years, how many <hi>Tuckneys, Stauntons, Reyners, Calamies, Newcomens, Greenhils, Bridges, Malories, Caryls, Nyes?</hi> And among others, how many <hi>young ones</hi> in the very <hi>Prime</hi> and <hi>Flower</hi> of their age, and <hi>heat</hi> of their work in the <hi>Lord's Vineyard,</hi> have been cropt off? How many <hi>Swinnocks, Sammſes, Allens, Woods, Blakes, Pearſes, Ste<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries, Loaders, Vennings, Janeways?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> The very <hi>few</hi> or <hi>almost none</hi> at all that have come up in the <hi>room</hi> of them nor (as things now ſtand) are like to do for the laſt <hi>fif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teen years</hi> together, where have any been found (ſetting the <hi>Confor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mable Clergy</hi> aſide) who have filled up the places of the foremention<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, either in <hi>Life</hi> or <hi>Doctrine,</hi> in <hi>Studies</hi> or <hi>Preaching,</hi> or in ſuch an <hi>elaborate care</hi> of Souls, as thoſe deceaſed <hi>Worthies</hi> underwent, even un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the death?</p>
            <p>Now of all others, ſhould not you the <hi>ſincere-hearted Profeſſors</hi> of the ſaid <hi>Reformed Proteſtant Religion,</hi> and the true lovers of it; you the <hi>Parents</hi> of Children, and you the <hi>Friends</hi> to other <hi>young Relations</hi> (eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecially,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:52086:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
(if <hi>numerous,</hi> or any way committed to your <hi>care</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>ſolicitous</hi> for their ſouls welfare now in this next following Age, and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>down to <hi>ſucceeding times?</hi> Would you not be willing that your Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and your Childrens Children ſhould be <hi>good Proteſtants?</hi> and in or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der thereunto, that <hi>ſound, able</hi> and <hi>faithful Proteſtant-Divines</hi> ſhould from time to time be <hi>bred</hi> up, to make up the <hi>loſs</hi> of ſuch as die daily? That <hi>young</hi> ones ſtill ſhould come up in the <hi>room</hi> of <hi>old</hi> ones, and ſo the <hi>Faith,</hi> which, as the Apoſtle ſaith (<hi>Jude</hi> 3.) <hi>was once delivered unto the Saints,</hi> ſhould be maintained in all future Generations? I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe you would; and if ſo, what <hi>better</hi> way can you think of to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vide ſuch, than what is ſuggeſted in this <hi>little Treatiſe?</hi> If you can find a <hi>better</hi> way, take it, and do your utmoſt in it; but do not <hi>imagine</hi> that you are no way <hi>concerned,</hi> and that the <hi>care</hi> of theſe matters lies <hi>upon God only,</hi> as if his will were not, that in this, as in all things elſe, we ſhould uſe all <hi>lawful</hi> and <hi>good</hi> means to attain the mercies we need, as well in <hi>Soul-concerns,</hi> as in thoſe of the <hi>Body.</hi> I know God will have a <hi>Church</hi> in all ages, and a <hi>ſelect People</hi> unto himſelf, <hi>pickt out</hi> and <hi>cull'd</hi> from the reſt of the world; and I know and believe further, that not one <hi>of his elect ſhall miſcarry</hi> or come ſhort of heaven. The Scriptures of Truth are full for theſe things, and by one means or another the <hi>all-wiſe</hi> and <hi>all-powerful God</hi> will effect them; and when <hi>ordinary</hi> means fail, he can and will make uſe of <hi>extraordinary.</hi> But this doth not <hi>exempt</hi> us from our duty and <hi>utmoſt endeavour</hi> to do our part; for in ſuch a <hi>neglect</hi> ſhall we not be found rather <hi>Tempters</hi> of God, than <hi>Truſters</hi> in him? 'Tis true, in former times, when <hi>deep Popery</hi> and the groſs dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it had <hi>thickned</hi> the Heavens over us, and even quite darkned all the <hi>European World,</hi> God was pleaſed here and there to raiſe up <hi>Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments</hi> in an <hi>extraordinary way</hi> to <hi>own, maintain</hi> and <hi>propagate</hi> the Truth in <hi>ſeveral Ages and Kingdoms.</hi> Thus about the <hi>thouſandth</hi> year after Chriſt, he was pleaſed to raiſe up one <hi>Leuthericus</hi> Archbiſhop of <hi>Senes</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> effectually to own and maintain the Truth in the point of <hi>Tranſubſtantiation,</hi> which he moſt <hi>ſtoutly oppoſed.</hi> And ſome time after him <hi>Beringarius,</hi> born at <hi>Towres</hi> in <hi>France,</hi> and conſtituted <hi>Arch-Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>con</hi> of <hi>Angeirs,</hi> defends the ſame Truth againſt <hi>Tranſubſtantiation</hi> with <hi>great</hi> boldneſs; and therein was followed by the <hi>French Proteſtants</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Hugonites.</hi> Then about 350 years after, he raiſed up our famous <hi>John Wi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>kliff</hi> of <hi>Merton-Colledge</hi> in <hi>Oxford,</hi> who in the days of our King <hi>Edward</hi> the <hi>Third,</hi> and <hi>Richard</hi> the <hi>Second,</hi> ſo notably diſcovered the <hi>Pope</hi> to be <hi>Antichriſt,</hi> and ſo ſtrenuouſly aſſerted and maintained the <hi>main Truths</hi> (which we <hi>Calviniſts</hi> now hold) that he was called
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:52086:18"/>
the <hi>Lamp of England.</hi> Some time after riſeth up our famous <hi>Bradwar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dine;</hi> and <hi>John Hus</hi> follows him in <hi>Bohemia;</hi> and <hi>Jerom</hi> of <hi>Prague</hi> fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows <hi>John Hus.</hi> Then <hi>Martin Luther</hi> about 100 years after, is fetched out of the Colledge of <hi>Auguſtin Monks</hi> at <hi>Erphord</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> him <hi>Deſiderius Eraſmus</hi> of <hi>Rotterdam</hi> (that <hi>Prodigy</hi> of <hi>Wit</hi> and <hi>Learning)</hi> de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fends. Next <hi>Huldericus Zuinglius</hi> of <hi>Tigurum</hi> among the <hi>Switzers. Oecolampadius</hi> of <hi>Weinſperge</hi> in <hi>Germany; <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus Regius</hi> in the Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ritories of <hi>Montfort; Caroloſtadius</hi> in <hi>France; Wolfgangus Capito</hi> in <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſatia; Leo Judae</hi> in <hi>Helvetia, Fredericus Myconius</hi> in <hi>Franconia; John Diazius,</hi> a <hi>Spaniſh Prieſt,</hi> and a great friend to <hi>Martin Bucer; Gaſper Cruciger</hi> of <hi>Lipſeich</hi> in <hi>Miſnia; Paulus Fagius,</hi> born in the <hi>Palatinate; Martin Bucer</hi> aforeſaid of <hi>Seleſtadt</hi> in <hi>Germany; Gaſper Hedio</hi> of <hi>Etlin</hi> in the Marquiſate of <hi>Baden; George Prince</hi> of <hi>Anhalt; Juſtus Jonas</hi> of <hi>Wittenberg</hi> in <hi>Germany;</hi> who having unwittingly eaten an <hi>Onion</hi> which his Father when ſick of the <hi>Plague,</hi> had applied to his <hi>Sore,</hi> was <hi>mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culouſly</hi> preſerved for the Service he was born unto; <hi>Peter Martyr</hi> of <hi>Florence</hi> in <hi>Italy; Conrade Pelican</hi> of <hi>Rubeac</hi> in <hi>Swedeland; Bugenhagi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us</hi> of <hi>Julinum</hi> in <hi>Pomerania, Philip Melancton</hi> of <hi>Bretta</hi> in the lower <hi>Palatinate; John Laſco</hi> of a Noble Family in <hi>Poland, Auguſtine Marlo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rat,</hi> born in the Dukedom of <hi>Lorrain,</hi> an <hi>Auguſtin Frier; Nicholas Amſdorſius,</hi> born of Noble Parents in <hi>Miſnia; Wolfangus Muſculus,</hi> born at <hi>Puſa,</hi> a little Town in <hi>Litharingia,</hi> and a <hi>Benedictine Monk</hi> in the <hi>Palatinate, Gerardus Hyperius</hi> at <hi>Iper</hi> in <hi>Flanders; John Calvin</hi> born at <hi>Noviodunum</hi> near the Borders of <hi>Picardy; Paulus Vergerius,</hi> Pope <hi>Clement</hi> the ſeventh his Legate in <hi>Germany; Victorinus Strigelius</hi> of <hi>Kausbira</hi> in <hi>Switzerland, John Brentius</hi> of <hi>Wile</hi> in <hi>Sweveland; Peter Viretus,</hi> born in the Countrey of the <hi>Bernates; Stephen Zegedine,</hi> born in the lower <hi>Panonia; Peter Ramus,</hi> born in <hi>France; Henry Bullinger,</hi> born at <hi>Bremagarta</hi> in <hi>Switzerland; Flavius Illiricus,</hi> born at <hi>Albona</hi> in <hi>Selavonia; Joſias Simlerus,</hi> born in <hi>Helvetia; Peter Boquin,</hi> born in <hi>Aquitane; Zacharias <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rſin,</hi> born in <hi>Sileſia; Abraham Bucholtzer,</hi> born at <hi>Scovanium; John Wigandus,</hi> born in <hi>Mansfield; Martin Chemnitius</hi> born at <hi>Britza</hi> in old <hi>March; Rodolphus Gualter,</hi> born in <hi>Tigure; Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſper Olevian,</hi> born in <hi>Trevir; George Stronius,</hi> born at <hi>Friburg</hi> in <hi>Wret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>law; James Andreas,</hi> born at <hi>Waiblin</hi> in <hi>Wittenberg; Hieronimus Zanchius,</hi> of a Noble Family in <hi>Italy; Anthony Sadel,</hi> born upon the Confines of <hi>Savoy,</hi> not far from <hi>Geneva; Lambertus Danaeus,</hi> born at <hi>Aurelia</hi> in <hi>France; Nicholas Hemingius,</hi> born at <hi>Loland</hi> in <hi>Denmark; Robert Rollock</hi> and <hi>John Knox,</hi> both born in <hi>Scotland; James Heer brand,</hi> born at <hi>Noricum</hi> in <hi>Swevia,</hi> for his <hi>early</hi> and <hi>late ſtudies</hi> called <hi>Suevica
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:52086:18"/>
Noctua,</hi> the <hi>Swevian</hi> Night-crow; <hi>David Chytraeus,</hi> born at <hi>Ingelfing</hi> in <hi>Sweveland; Daniel Toſſanus,</hi> born at <hi>Moumbelgard</hi> in <hi>Wirtemberg; Franciſcus Junius,</hi> and <hi>Theodora Bezus,</hi> born in <hi>France; Amandus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lanus,</hi> born in <hi>Sileſia; Andraeas Gerardus,</hi> born at <hi>Hypeirs</hi> in <hi>Flanders; Aretius Benedictus,</hi> born at <hi>Berne</hi> in <hi>Switzerland; John Druſius,</hi> born at <hi>Aldnard</hi> near the City of <hi>Gaunt; James Gerynaeus,</hi> born at <hi>Berne</hi> in <hi>Helvetia.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>All theſe famous men (as they are reckoned up by <hi>Melchior Adam, Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler,</hi> and others) as well thoſe which are here named before <hi>Luther,</hi> as thoſe that are reckoned up <hi>after him,</hi> and were born ſome time within the <hi>Sixteenth Century,</hi> were at firſt <hi>born in Popery,</hi> and in their younger times were trained up in it; but being all of them men of <hi>admirable Natural Parts, great Students,</hi> and <hi>ſingularly well learned,</hi> were touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed with <hi>Divine Powers,</hi> enlightned and warmed with <hi>Divine Beams</hi> of <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>Love</hi> of it, and thereupon <hi>forſook</hi> their <hi>Popiſh Principles,</hi> ſome <hi>in part</hi> only, ſome <hi>wholly</hi> and throughout, and were by <hi>extraor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary calls</hi> from God, ſet up as <hi>glorious Lights</hi> in the <hi>dark times</hi> and <hi>places</hi> when and where they lived; God himſelf <hi>plucking</hi> them, as it were, like <hi>Firebrands out of the Fire,</hi> with a purpoſe to make an honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable <hi>uſe</hi> of their <hi>Parts, Learning</hi> and <hi>Grace,</hi> againſt <hi>Popery</hi> and all manner of <hi>Popiſh Sects</hi> and <hi>Orders,</hi> as <hi>Monks, Prieſts, Friers, Jeſuits,</hi> and their <hi>deteſtable</hi> Doctrines. And as he did this <hi>abroad,</hi> in the <hi>ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Countries</hi> abovenamed, ſo here in our own <hi>Native Countrey;</hi> did he not in the <hi>ſame</hi> times, I mean in the ſame 16th <hi>Century</hi> raiſe up many <hi>worthy</hi> men, <hi>famous</hi> alſo for their both <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Learning;</hi> and not only <hi>convert</hi> them after their <hi>popiſh education,</hi> but make <hi>eminent uſe</hi> of them as <hi>valiant Champions, Confeſſors</hi> and <hi>Martyrs</hi> for the Truth, <hi>viz. John Colet</hi> of <hi>London, John Frith</hi> of <hi>Weſtram</hi> in <hi>Kent, William Tyndal, Thomas Bilney, John Rogers,</hi> the <hi>Proto-Martyr</hi> in Queen <hi>Maries</hi> dayes; <hi>Laurence Sanders, John Bradford, John Hooper, Hugh Latimer, Nicholas Ridley, Thomas Cranmer, Rowland Taylor, John Philpot, John Jewel, John Reynolds, John Fox,</hi> and many more which might be added. I ſay, though God did this, and can do the like again in an <hi>extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> way; though he can open the eyes of thoſe <hi>learned</hi> men in this our <hi>preſent age,</hi> and <hi>turn</hi> their hearts from the <hi>Error</hi> of their wayes, who are now <hi>deeply dren hed</hi> in the Doctrines of <hi>Pelagianiſm, Arminianiſm, Socinianiſm, Popery,</hi> or whatſoever it is that borders upon any one of them; though he can find out an <hi>Ambroſe,</hi> by his preaching to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert an <hi>Auſtin,</hi> with the help of the <hi>Prayers</hi> and <hi>Tears</hi> of his Mother <hi>Monica;</hi> though by one man's <hi>Books</hi> he can <hi>convert</hi> another, as he did
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:52086:19"/>
               <hi>Martin Bucer, Paulus Vergerius, Caroloſtadius, Leo Judae, Zuinglius</hi> his companion in Studies; <hi>Fredericus Myconius, John Diazius</hi> a <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> Prieſt; <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>rbanus Rhegius, Wolfangus Muſculus,</hi> and many other <hi>Famous</hi> men in <hi>Germany,</hi> by reading of <hi>Luthers</hi> works. I ſay, though by theſe and many other wayes, he can raiſe up <hi>inſtruments</hi> even from men of the <hi>preſent age,</hi> and now in the very <hi>Prime</hi> and <hi>Flower</hi> of their <hi>Parts</hi> and <hi>Learning,</hi> cauſe them to <hi>return</hi> to <hi>ſound Doctrine!</hi> whatever their preſent <hi>Errors</hi> may be) and <hi>ſtrenuouſly</hi> to <hi>maintain</hi> it againſt <hi>Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> and other <hi>prevailing corruptions</hi> in Doctrine or otherwiſe: Yet no man in his <hi>right ſenſes</hi> will deny but that it is every <hi>good Proteſtants duty,</hi> in his <hi>place</hi> and <hi>calling,</hi> and as <hi>opportunity</hi> may be providentially <hi>given</hi> to him, or <hi>taken</hi> by him, to do his <hi>utmoſt</hi> for providing a <hi>ſtanding</hi> and alwayes <hi>ſucceeding Miniſtry</hi> in the <hi>uſual</hi> and <hi>ordinary</hi> way of <hi>Education of hopeful Youths in Schools of Learning,</hi> which is the thing that in this ſmall Treatiſe I <hi>principally</hi> preſs unto. And therefore to conclude all, ſince the <hi>Scriptures</hi> both of the <hi>Old</hi> and <hi>New Teſtament</hi> declare it to be a moſt <hi>bleſſed thing to convert Souls,</hi> and to bring in ſinners to <hi>Chriſt's Fold,</hi> as is evident by comparing <hi>Dan.</hi> 12.3. with <hi>Luke</hi> 1.14, 18. <hi>Eph.</hi> 3.7, 8. with many other pregnant Texts that might be added to the ſame purpoſe; I Query,</p>
            <p n="1">1. Whether the <hi>Work</hi> of the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> where it is <hi>faithfully</hi> and <hi>ſincerely</hi> diſcharged by <hi>able, orthodox</hi> and <hi>painful Labourers</hi> in Chriſt's Vineyard, and is accompanied with an <hi>anſwerable ſucceſs,</hi> or at leaſt finds a <hi>gracious acceptance</hi> with Chriſt, be not a <hi>very honourable,</hi> and (to all <hi>conſiderate</hi> good men) a very <hi>deſirable</hi> employment? and whether thoſe <hi>Parents</hi> and their <hi>Children</hi> that <hi>undervalue, deſpiſe</hi> and <hi>ſcorn</hi> it as a <hi>mean</hi> and <hi>contemptible</hi> courſe of Life, may not well expect to be <hi>ſcorn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed</hi> of God, and for ever to be <hi>rejected</hi> by him?</p>
            <p n="2">2. Although the <hi>Miniſtry</hi> and the work thereof be ſo <hi>honourable</hi> an employment, as willingly to be undertaken and <hi>delighted</hi> in by ſuch as the Lord inclines unto it and <hi>qualifies</hi> for it; yet whether they ought not to be <hi>encouraged</hi> and <hi>rewarded</hi> for their faithful and painful Labours therein, even to the <hi>utmoſt power</hi> and <hi>ability</hi> of thoſe that ſit under them, and have the <hi>benefit</hi> thereof? For doth not Chriſt himſelf ſay, <hi>The Labourer is worthy of his hire,</hi> Luke 10.7. and the <hi>Workman of his Meat,</hi> Mat. 10.10. and this, though he be otherwiſe <hi>rich,</hi> and hath no need? And much more then muſt it not needs be true of all ſuch <hi>faithful</hi> and <hi>painful Miniſters,</hi> as having Wives, Children and Families to maintain, have nothing elſe to live upon but what comes in <hi>this way?</hi> Let all that are concerned herein, read and conſider well 1 <hi>Cor.</hi>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:52086:19"/>
9.13, 14. <hi>Do ye not know that they which miniſter about holy things, live of the things of the Temple? and they that wait at the Altar, are parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers with the Altar? even ſo hath the Lord ordained, that they which preach the Goſpel, ſhould live of the Goſpel.</hi> And that in 1 Tim. 5.17. <hi>Let the Elders that rule well be counted worthy of double honour</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap>, double reward) <hi>eſpecially they who labour in Word and Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But when and where <hi>worthy</hi> and <hi>able</hi> men are found, that with the <hi>peace</hi> of their own <hi>Conſciences,</hi> cannot be capable of publick mainte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance through their <hi>Nonconformity in matters Eccleſiaſtical;</hi> and the well-minded <hi>Proteſtant-Party</hi> every where, by <hi>perſecutions,</hi> are (for the moſt part) ſo far impoveriſhed, ruined and <hi>undone,</hi> that they are not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to give a livelihood to ſuch as preach unto them; would it not be a <hi>worthy work,</hi> and exceedingly well pleaſing unto God, if ſuch <hi>rich ones</hi> among them, as are yet left able to do it, would take care ſo far to <hi>miniſter</hi> to them, and <hi>allow</hi> them ſuch a <hi>maintenance</hi> as might <hi>encourage</hi> them in their work, in the midſt of all that <hi>oppoſition</hi> which they meet with from <hi>unreaſonable</hi> and <hi>ill-minded</hi> men?</p>
            <p n="4">4. Whether all ſuch <hi>rich Proteſtants</hi> as are mentioned in the forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Treatiſe, that have Sons of their own, of <hi>pregnant Parts,</hi> apt to learn, and by perſwaſions of them their Parents, would eaſily <hi>be incli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned</hi> to the Service of <hi>Chriſt</hi> in the aforeſaid <hi>glorious work</hi> of the Miniſtry, or in caſe they have no ſuch Sons of their own, yet would pleaſe to adopt ſuch as are in the ſaid <hi>Treatiſe</hi> already ſuggeſted, and not only bring them up to the ſaid <hi>Service,</hi> in manner as is propounded; but ſettle a <hi>liberal maintenance</hi> upon them during their lives, at leaſt, in caſe they continue <hi>ſound</hi> in the Faith, <hi>painful</hi> in their Work, and <hi>holy</hi> in their Converſations: I ſay, whether thoſe that ſhall do ſuch a <hi>noble work</hi> as this, beſides the giving proof of their <hi>Love</hi> to Chriſt, they will not by this means render the Children which they thus bring up &amp; dedicate to the <hi>Lord's work,</hi> and ſettle Eſtates upon them in conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of it (whether they be their <hi>own Children</hi> or ſuch as are <hi>adopetd</hi> by them) I ſay, whether they will not render them <hi>doubly happy?</hi> Firſt, in putting them into ſo <hi>honourable</hi> and <hi>heavenly</hi> an employment? Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>condly, In delivering them from the <hi>Snares</hi> and <hi>Temptations</hi> they would otherwiſe be endangered by, if not <hi>thus</hi> provided for, upon account of their <hi>faithfulneſs</hi> and <hi>conſtancy</hi> in their work, whatſoever diſcourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments and troubles they may meet with for their <hi>works ſake?</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="5">5. Whether it would not be one of the moſt Glorious works that ſome Ages have produced, if certain <hi>rich Proteſtants,</hi> amongſt others the
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:52086:20"/>
aforementioned Acts of <hi>Piety</hi> humbly moved to be promoted by them, here in <hi>Old England,</hi> ſhould agree together to ſet<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>le a perpetual <hi>liberal maintenance</hi> upon the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſity</hi> of <hi>Cambridge</hi> in <hi>New-England,</hi> and ſo to endow it; that it might be a <hi>ſtanding</hi> and <hi>laſting Nurſery</hi> to all <hi>ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding Ages,</hi> not only to train up ſuch hopeful and <hi>well educated</hi> Youths for the ſervice of the <hi>Goſpel</hi> there, as ſhall be born in that <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey;</hi> but ſuch alſo as ſhall be ſent from <hi>hence</hi> for the ſame purpoſe, in due t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>me to return hither <hi>richly furniſhed</hi> with ſound Learning and abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lities to do the like ſervice here? Methinks 50 or 60 (if not 100) per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons might eaſily be found in this <hi>Kingdom</hi> of <hi>Old-England,</hi> that might each of them give an <hi>hundred pounds</hi> a year for ever to the ſaid <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity</hi> in <hi>New Eng<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and,</hi> for ſo <hi>pious</hi> and <hi>renowned</hi> a work, and thereby not only <hi>perpetuate</hi> and <hi>embalm</hi> their <hi>Names</hi> here, but prepare the more <hi>abundant entrance for themſelves into the Kingdom of our Lord and Saviour Jeſus Christ,</hi> and ſo be he higher in happineſs hereafter. For though I am far from that <hi>Popiſh Opinion</hi> of Merit (whether of <hi>condignity</hi> or <hi>con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gruity</hi>) and do not in the leaſt think that any man whatſoev<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>an <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve</hi> any thing at the hand of God for any good work or work that can be done by him; yet that <hi>every one receives according to his w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>ks,</hi> is no falſe Doctrine, if thoſe Scriptures be true in 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.10. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 14.13. &amp; 20.12, 13.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Whether this ſmall Treatiſe, if it ſhall be judged <hi>uſeful</hi> and <hi>ſeaſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nable,</hi> will not be ſo moſt of all by being <hi>diſperſed abroad</hi> into many hands, and into thoſe principally that it is <hi>more particularly intended for,</hi> as into the hands of all <hi>diſſenting</hi> (though ſound in the main) <hi>true-hearted Profeſſors;</hi> into the hands of the <hi>Parents</hi> and <hi>Governors</hi> of <hi>nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous Families;</hi> into the hands of the ſeveral ſorts of the aforementioned <hi>rich Proteſtants;</hi> into the hands of <hi>all religiouſly affected young perſons,</hi> eſpecially ſuch as are under the age of ſixteen years? And whether it would not be Money well laid out to <hi>print ſo many Impreſſions,</hi> and take care and pains to <hi>diſperſe</hi> them, as might repleniſh all the aforeſaid Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in theſe <hi>Three Kingdoms</hi> of <hi>England, Scotland</hi> and <hi>Ireland?</hi> Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>haps <hi>ſome</hi> of the things humbly propoſed in the Treatiſe, may take with <hi>ſome, others with others;</hi> ſome may be prevailed with by it, to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicate their <hi>own Sons</hi> to the Service of the <hi>Sanctuary;</hi> ſome to <hi>adopt</hi> o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers; ſome that cannot, or have no mind to do this, may ſettle <hi>Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey-Schools,</hi> and give <hi>yearly Stipends</hi> for teaching <hi>poor Children</hi> to read, in <hi>great</hi> and <hi>populous Towns,</hi> and where is greateſt <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>leaſt Means</hi> for Knowledge in the <hi>remote</hi> and <hi>dark parts</hi> of the Kingdoms particularly in the <hi>Northern</hi> and <hi>Weſtern</hi> Parts, and all over <hi>Wales?</hi>
            </p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:52086:20"/>
               <head>A Paſſage out of Mr. <hi>Increaſe Mather</hi> his Excellent Book, En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tituled, <hi>The Myſtery of</hi> Iſrael's <hi>Salvation.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>And ſhall I tell you (yea from the Lord I will tell you) that the Prayers of the deſpicable ones, that know, and fear, and ſerve God, can do great things with him that doth <hi>whatſoever he pleaſeth in Heaven, and in Earth, and in all deep places.</hi> Oh conſider of it! I remember <hi>Melancthon</hi> (that great and Learned Divine) ſaith, <q>he was much en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couraged to hope that God would carry on the work of Reformation in <hi>Germany</hi> (and the Lord did carry it on with great ſucceſs in thoſe days) becauſe he underſtood that there were many poor Godly wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men that were wont to meet together to pray, that the work of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation might go forward.</q> Even ſo, if the Lord ſtir up the hearts of his poor Saints to favour the duſt of <hi>Zion,</hi> and to ſhew it by earneſt Prayer before him at all times; ſurely the day will not be long before the <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rd appear in his Glory to build up</hi> Zion; for he will <hi>have rgard unto the Prayer of the deſtitute, and will not deſpiſe their Prayer.</hi> Thus far he at the very cloſe of his Book. The ſame ſay I here; Fervent Prayer all <hi>England</hi> over among ſuch as truly fear the Lord, and know how to pray aright, may poſſibly ſet hundreds on work to help on the ends of this ſmall Treatiſe, and the Matters propounded in it.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
